<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The line of proportion or numbers, commonly called Gunters line, made easie by the which may be measured all manner of superficies and solids, as board, glass, pavement, timber, stone, &amp;c. : also, how to perform the same by a line of equal parts ... : whereunto is added, the use of the line of proportion improved ... / by William Leybourn.</title>
            <author>Leybourn, William, 1626-1716.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1667</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 137 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 92 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A48340</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing L1916</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R18369</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12349647</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12349647</idno>
            <idno type="VID">59941</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A48340)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 59941)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 215:13)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The line of proportion or numbers, commonly called Gunters line, made easie by the which may be measured all manner of superficies and solids, as board, glass, pavement, timber, stone, &amp;c. : also, how to perform the same by a line of equal parts ... : whereunto is added, the use of the line of proportion improved ... / by William Leybourn.</title>
                  <author>Leybourn, William, 1626-1716.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[6], 16, [2], 153 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by J.S. for G. Sawbridge ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1667.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>First ed. Cf. BM.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Slide-rule.</term>
               <term>Mathematical instruments --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Mensuration --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-10</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2009-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>Pip Willcox</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:59941:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:59941:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The LINE of PROPORTION or NUMBERS, Commonly called Gunters Line, Made Eaſie. By the which may be Meaſured all manner of <hi>Superficies</hi> and <hi>Solids,</hi> as <hi>Board, Glaſs, Pavement, Timber, Stone,</hi> &amp;c.</p>
            <p>ALSO, How to perform the ſame by a Line of Equal Parts, drawn from the Centre of a Two-Foot-Rule.</p>
            <p>Whereunto is added, The Uſe of the Line of Proportion Improved: Whereby all manner of <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficies</hi> and <hi>Solids,</hi> may both exactly and ſpeedily be meaſured, without the help of Pen or Compaſſes, by Inſpection, looking only upon the Ruler.</p>
            <p>By WILLIAM LEYBOURN.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>J. S.</hi> for <hi>G. Sawbridge,</hi> at his Houſe on <hi>Clerkenwell-green.</hi> 1667.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="license_to_print">
            <pb facs="tcp:59941:2"/>
            <p>LICENSED,</p>
            <closer>
               <dateline>
                  <date>
                     <hi>Nov.</hi> 9. 1666.</date>
               </dateline>
               <signed>Roger L' Eſtrange.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:59941:2"/>
            <p>To the Right Honourable Sir WILLIAM BOLTON Knight, Lord Major of the City of <hi>London.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Right Worſhipful the Alder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men of the ſame City.</p>
            <p>As alſo to
<list>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>JOHN AUSTEN</item>
                        <item>and THOMAS NEVILE</item>
                     </list> Eſquires.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>Commoners, Appoined by a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mittee of Common-Council to direct the Admeaſurement of the Ruines by the late Fire there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>WILLIAM LEYBOURN,</hi>
            </p>
            <p>One of thoſe Employed by Order in the Survey of thoſe Ruines, Humbly pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſents (with the beſt of his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices) this Manual.</p>
            <p>Neceſſary for all Builders, and thoſe that ſhall Employ them.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:59941:3"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>THE Line of Proportion or Numbers, commonly called (by Artificers) <hi>Gunter's Line,</hi> hath been diſcourſed of by ſeveral perſons, and variouſly applied to divers uſes; for when Mr. <hi>Gunter</hi> had brought it from the Tables to a Line, and written ſome Uſes thereof, Mr. <hi>Wingate</hi> added divers Lines of ſeveral lengths, thereby to Extract the Square or Cube Roots, without doubling or trebling the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtaence of the Compaſſes: After him Mr. <hi>Milbourn</hi> a <hi>Yorkſhire</hi> Gentle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man diſpoſed it in a Serpentine or Spiral Line, thereby enlarging the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions of the Line. Again, Mr. <hi>Seth Partrîdge</hi> contrived two Rulers,
<pb facs="tcp:59941:3"/>to ſlide one by the ſide of the other, having upon them two Lines of one length, which exactly and readily per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formeth all Operations wrought there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by, very exactly and ſpeedily, without the help of Compaſſes.</p>
            <p>Now whatſoever all the forementi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oned Contrivances will perform, I have here ſhewed in this Manual, and ſo ordered the Line that it will per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the work without Compaſſes, by Inſpection, looking only upon the Ruler. And thereby may be meaſured (let the Line be of what length ſoever) not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Board, Glaſs, Timber,</hi> and <hi>Stone,</hi> but alſo all manner of <hi>Hangings, Pavements, VVainſcots, Plaiſtering, Tyling, Brick-work,</hi> &amp;c. To all which Uſes I have particularly applied it, as will appear by ſeveral Inſtances in all the forementioned particulars; and the rather, becauſe this Treatiſe may be beneficial and uſeful as well to Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tlemen and others (who at this time may
<pb facs="tcp:59941:4"/>have more than ordinary occaſion to make uſe thereof, in the Re-building of the Renowned City of <hi>London,</hi>) as to Artificers themſelves, for whoſe ſakes chiefly it was intended.</p>
            <closer>
               <salute>Vale.</salute>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="advert_for_mathematical_instruments_etc.">
            <head>ADVERTISEMENT.</head>
            <p>IF any Gentleman ſtudious in the Mathematicks, have or ſhall have occaſion for Inſtruments thereunto belonging, or Books to ſhew the uſe of them, they may be furniſhed with all ſorts, uſeful both for Sea or Land. either in Silver, Braſs, or VVood, by <hi>Walter Hayes</hi> at the <hi>Croſs-Daggers</hi> in <hi>Moor-fields,</hi> next door to the <hi>Popes-head</hi> Tavern; where they may have all ſorts of Maps, Globes, Sea-plats, and Mathematical Paper, Carpenters Rules; Poſt and Pocket-Dials for any Latitude, Steel Letters, Figures, Signs, Planets, or Aſpects, at reaſonable Rates.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div n="plain rule" type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59941:4"/>
            <head>How to Meaſure Board and Timber BY THE Carpenters PLAIN RULE.</head>
            <p>ALL manner of Superficial and Solid Meaſures may be meaſured the moſt abſolute and artificial ways that are yet known, by the Precepts and Examples in this Book delivered: But although, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Capacity may not attain to the knowledg and underſtanding thereof, I thought good here to inſert the Uſe of that Rule which is commonly made and ſold, and which every Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificer
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59941:5"/>continually carries about him.</p>
            <div type="description">
               <head>Its Deſcription.</head>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <head>I. <hi>Of the FORE-SIDE.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>It conſiſteth of two flat ſides, one of which towards either edge there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is divided into 24 equal parts called Inches, and numbered by 1, 2, 3, 4, and ſo forth to 24 at the end thereof: Every one of the parts or Inches is again divided into two equal parts by Lines about half the length of the other, repreſenting half Inch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es; and every of theſe half Inches is divided into two other equal parts, called quarters of Inches; and each of thoſe again into two other equal parts, called half quarters of Inches: So that each Inch is divided into eight equal parts, repreſenting Inches, Halves, Quarters, and Half-quarters.</p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:59941:5"/>
                  <p>Both the edges on the one ſide of the Rule are thus divided and num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bered, only where 24 ſtands at one end of the Line on one edge, there 1 ſtands on the other edge; ſo that which end of the Rule ſoever you meaſure with, you may count your number of Inches and parts right, without turn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of the Rule.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II. <hi>Of the BACK-SIDE.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>On the other ſide of the Rule you have two other Lines or Scales drawn neer to the edges of the ſame ſide; one is called the <hi>Line of Board-Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure,</hi> the other the <hi>Line of Timber-Meaſure.</hi> At the beginning of ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther of theſe Lines you have a little Table of Figures, the one for <hi>Board,</hi> the other for <hi>Timber</hi> or <hi>Stone.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The line or Scale of <hi>Board-Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure</hi> begins at 6 towards your left hand, and ſo goes on to 36, ending
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59941:6"/>juſt 4 Inches ſhort of the other end of the Rule; but ſometimes this Line is continued up to 100, but nor often, and then it goes nearer to the end of the Rule, namely, to within an Inch and an half of the end there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of. At the beginning of this Line there is a ſmall Table from 1, to 6 In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, which ſhews (in Figures) the quantity of the length of a Foot of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Board from one Inch broad to 6 Inches broad, and then the diviſions ſupply the greater breadths.</p>
                  <p>On the other edge, on the ſame ſide you have the Line or Scale of Timber-meaſure. This Scale begins at 8 and an half, and ſo goes on, (by diviſions) to 36, towards the other end of the Ruler, namely, 36 end<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing within almoſt an Inch and half of the Rules end. To this Scale alſo there belongeth a Table, which ſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth at the beginning of the Line, and goes from 1 Inch to 8 Inches, and
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59941:6"/>gives the quantity of the length of a Foot of any Timber under 8 Inches ſquare in Figures, as the other did for Board from 1 to 6: And theſe are called the <hi>Tables of Under-meaſure.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <head>The Table for UNDER-BOARD-MEASURE.</head>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1</cell>
                           <cell>2</cell>
                           <cell>3</cell>
                           <cell>4</cell>
                           <cell>5</cell>
                           <cell>6</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>12</cell>
                           <cell>6</cell>
                           <cell>4</cell>
                           <cell>3</cell>
                           <cell>2</cell>
                           <cell>2</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                           <cell>4</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <head>The Table for UNDER-TIMBER-MEASURE.</head>
                        <row>
                           <cell>1</cell>
                           <cell>2</cell>
                           <cell>3</cell>
                           <cell>4</cell>
                           <cell>5</cell>
                           <cell>6</cell>
                           <cell>7</cell>
                           <cell>8</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>144</cell>
                           <cell>36</cell>
                           <cell>16</cell>
                           <cell>9</cell>
                           <cell>5</cell>
                           <cell>4</cell>
                           <cell>2</cell>
                           <cell>2</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                           <cell>9</cell>
                           <cell>0</cell>
                           <cell>11</cell>
                           <cell>3</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="application">
               <argument>
                  <p>Thus much for the Deſcription of
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:59941:7"/>the Lines upon the Carpenters plain Rule: Now for</p>
               </argument>
               <head>Their Uſe.</head>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>I.</hi> Of the <hi>Fore-ſide,</hi> or Side of <hi>Inches.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>This ſide is only to meaſure the length and breadth of any thing to be meaſured, in Inches and parts; the manner of doing whereof is natural to every man; for, taking the Rule in the left hand, apply it to the thing to be meaſured, ſo have you the length, breadth, or thickneſs of the thing de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired. But,</p>
                  <pb n="7" facs="tcp:59941:7"/>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>
                     <hi>II.</hi> Of the <hi>Backſide.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>and,</p>
                  <div n="1" type="part">
                     <head>
                        <hi>I.</hi> Of the Line of <hi>Board-meaſure.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div n="1" type="problem">
                        <head>
                           <hi>PROB. 1.</hi> The breadth of any Board being given, to finde how much there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in length will make a Foot ſquare.</head>
                        <p>Look for the number of Inches that your Board (or Glaſs) is broad, in the Line of Board-meaſure; and the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Inches and parts of an Inch which ſtand againſt that on the other ſide of your Rule, is the quantity of Inches that will make a Foot ſquare of that Board, or Glaſs, or what other thing ſoever it be to be meaſured.</p>
                        <pb n="8" facs="tcp:59941:8"/>
                        <p>Example 1. <hi>There is a Board or Plank that is</hi> 9 <hi>Inches broad, how much of that in length will make a Foot ſquare?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Look for 9 Inches upon the Line of Board-meaſure (which you ſhall finde at the Figure 9 upon the ſame Line), and juſt againſt that, on the other ſide of your Rule you ſhall finde 16 Inch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, which ſhews that every 16 Inches of that piece in length, will make a Foot ſquare.</p>
                        <p>Example 2. <hi>A Pain of Glaſs is</hi> 22 <hi>Inches broad, how much thereof in length will make a Foot ſquare?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Look for 22 Inches in the Line of Board-meaſure, and right againſt it (on the other ſide of your Rule) you ſhall finde 6 Inches and almoſt an half; and ſo much in length of that breadth will make a Foot ſquare.</p>
                        <pb n="9" facs="tcp:59941:8"/>
                        <p>Example 3. <hi>If any plain Superfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies be</hi> 30 <hi>Inches broad, how much thereof in length will make a Foot ſquare?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Seek for 30 Inches in the Line of Board-meaſure, and right againſt it, on the other ſide of the Rule, you ſhall finde 4 Inches and ⅘, that is, 4 Inches and 4 fifth parts of an Inch.</p>
                        <p>Example 4. <hi>If a Board be</hi> 9 <hi>Inches and an half broad, how much thereof in length will make a Poot ſquare?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Seek 9 Inches and an half in the Line of Board-meaſure, and againſt that on the other ſide of the Rule you ſhall finde 15 Inches and about one ſixth part of an Inch, to make a Foot ſquare.</p>
                        <p>¶ <hi>NOTE.</hi> All theſe Examples might be performed otherwiſe by the Line; for if you take the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59941:9"/>Rule in your left hand, and ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply the end thereof noted with 36 to the end of the Superficies, the other edge of the Superfici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es will ſhew how many Inches, Halves, and Quarters will make a Foot ſquare. This needs no Example.</p>
                     </div>
                     <div n="2" type="problem">
                        <head>
                           <hi>PROB. 2.</hi> The length and breadth of a Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies being given, to finde how many Square Feet are therein contained?</head>
                        <p>By any of the ways before taught) finde how much of the breadth gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven will make a Foot ſquare; then run that length from one of the ends of the Superficies as often as you can, and ſo many ſquare feet is there in that Superficies</p>
                        <pb n="11" facs="tcp:59941:9"/>
                        <p>Example. <hi>A Board is</hi> 9 <hi>Inches <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                                 <desc>•</desc>
                              </gap>road and</hi> 15 <hi>Poot long, how many ſquare Feet are therein contained?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>By the firſt Example you finde that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                              <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                           </gap> 9 Inches broad, 16 Inches in length to make a Foot; wherefore take 16 Inches of your Rule, and run that length along the Board from one end thereof, and you ſhall finde that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ength to be contained in the Board of 15 Foot long, 11 times and 4 Inches over, which is ¼ of a Foot; ſo that the Board of 15 Foot long and 9 In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches broad, contains 11 Foot and one quarter: The like of any other.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="part">
                     <head>II. Of the Line of <hi>Timber-meaſure.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <div n="1" type="problem">
                        <head>
                           <hi>PROBL. 1.</hi> The Square of any piece of Timber at the end thereof being given, to finde how much of that piece in length ſhall make a Foot ſolid?</head>
                        <pb n="12" facs="tcp:59941:10"/>
                        <p>The Uſe of the Line of Timber-meaſure is in all reſpects the ſame at that of Board-meaſure; for knowing the ſquare of your piece of Timber at the end thereof, you have no more to do than to look for the quantity of the Square thereof in the Line of Timber-meaſure, and right againſt it, on the other ſide of the Rule, you have the quantity of Inches that will make a Foot ſolid of that piece.</p>
                        <p>Example 1. <hi>A piece of Timber is</hi> 10 <hi>Inches ſquare, how much thereof in length will make a Foot ſolid?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Look for 10 Inches in the Line of Timber-meaſure, and right againſt it, on the other ſide of the Rule, you ſhall finde 17 Inches and ſomewhat above a quarter of an Inch; and ſo much of that piece in length will make a Foot ſolid.</p>
                        <pb n="13" facs="tcp:59941:10"/>
                        <p>Example 2. <hi>If the Square of a piece of Timber be</hi> 21 <hi>Inches, how much thereof in length will make a Foot ſolid?</hi>
                        </p>
                        <p>Seek 21 Inches in the Line of Timber-meaſure, and againſt it you ſhall finde, on the other ſide of the Rule, almoſt 4 Inches; and ſo much in length will make a ſolid Foot of Timber.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Note</hi> 1. If Timber be broader at one end then at the other, the uſual way is to add both ends together, and take half thereof for the true ſquare; but if the difference be very much, this way is erroneous, though for the moſt part practiſed.</p>
                        <p>
                           <hi>Note</hi> 2. Alſo for Round Timber, the uſual way is to girt it about the middle with a String, and take a fourth part thereof for the Square; this alſo is erroneous: Therefore for ſuch as
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:59941:11"/>deſire curioſity and exactneſs, let them repair to the Rules in this Book delivered for that purpoſe, where they may receive ample ſatisfaction.</p>
                     </div>
                  </div>
                  <div type="part">
                     <head>Concerning the <hi>Tables</hi> at the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the <hi>Lines</hi> of <hi>Board</hi> and <hi>Timber-Meaſure.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>The Table of Board-Meaſure gives the length of a Foot ſquare of any Board under 6 Inches broad; there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore by the Table there ſet you may finde that
<table>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell role="label">
                                 <hi>Foot.</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell role="label">
                                 <hi>In.</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell role="label">
                                 <hi>parts.</hi>
                              </cell>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell> </cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell rows="7">If a Board be</cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                              <cell rows="7">Inches broad</cell>
                              <cell>12</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell rows="7">will make a Foot ſquare.</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>6</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>5</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                              <cell>5</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>6</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </p>
                     <p>By this ſmall Table you may ſee, that a Board of 4 Inches broad will require 3 Foot thereof in length to
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59941:11"/>make a Foot ſquare.—Alſo, a Board of 5 Inches broad will require 2 Foot 4 Inches and 4 fifth parts of an Inch.</p>
                     <p>The Table of Timber-meaſure gives the length of a Foot folid of any piece of Timber or Stone whoſe ſquare is under 8 Inches: Wherefore by the Table at the beginning of the Line of Timber-meaſure you may finde that
<table>
                           <row>
                              <cell rows="8">If a piece of Timber be</cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                              <cell rows="8">Inch quare</cell>
                              <cell>256</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell rows="8">will make a Foot ſolid.</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>36</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                              <cell>16</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                              <cell>9</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>5</cell>
                              <cell>5</cell>
                              <cell>9</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>6</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>7</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>11</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>8</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </p>
                     <p>By this Table (which is the ſame in effect with that which ſtandeth at the end of the Line of Timber-meaſure) you may ſee that a piece of Timber that is 4 Inches ſquare requires 9 Foot in length to make a ſolid Foot: Alſo, a pitce of 5 Inches ſquare, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:59941:12"/>5 Foot 9 Inches and 1/16 parts of an Inch to make a ſolid Foot: And ſo of the reſt.</p>
                     <p>But becauſe theſe Tables go only to whole Inches, I have here added two Tables, one for Board, the other for Timber; the Table for Board, from one quarter of an Inch to 6 In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in breadth; and the Table for Timber, from 2. Inches ſquare to 8 Inches, by Inches, Halves, and Quar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>The Tables follow.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb facs="tcp:59941:12"/>
                     <p>
                        <table>
                           <head>The Table for Board-meaſure.</head>
                           <row>
                              <cell role="label" cols="2">Inches &amp; qu.</cell>
                              <cell role="label">feet.</cell>
                              <cell role="label">in.</cell>
                              <cell role="label">10 par.</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                              <cell>48</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>24</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                              <cell>16</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>I.</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>12</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                              <cell>9</cell>
                              <cell>7</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>8</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                              <cell>6</cell>
                              <cell>10</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>II.</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>6</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                              <cell>5</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                              <cell>9</cell>
                              <cell>6</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>III.</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell role="label" cols="2">Inches &amp; qu.</cell>
                              <cell role="label">feet.</cell>
                              <cell role="label">in.</cell>
                              <cell role="label">10 par.</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>III.</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                              <cell>8</cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                              <cell>5</cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>IV.</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>9</cell>
                              <cell>9</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>8</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>6</cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>V.</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                              <cell>8</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <table>
                           <head>The Table for Timber-meaſure.</head>
                           <row>
                              <cell>II.</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>36</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                              <cell>28</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>23</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                              <cell>19</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>III.</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>16</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                              <cell>13</cell>
                              <cell>7</cell>
                              <cell>6</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>11</cell>
                              <cell>9</cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                              <cell>10</cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                              <cell>8</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>IV.</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>9</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                              <cell>7</cell>
                              <cell>11</cell>
                              <cell>6</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>7</cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                              <cell>6</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                              <cell>6</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>V.</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>5</cell>
                              <cell>9</cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                              <cell>5</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>7</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                              <cell>9</cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>VI.</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                              <cell>9</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                              <cell>9</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell>VII.</cell>
                              <cell>0</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>11</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>8</cell>
                              <cell>1</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>6</cell>
                              <cell>7</cell>
                           </row>
                           <row>
                              <cell> </cell>
                              <cell>3</cell>
                              <cell>2</cell>
                              <cell>4</cell>
                              <cell>7</cell>
                           </row>
                        </table>
                     </p>
                  </div>
                  <div type="instruction_to_printer">
                     <pb facs="tcp:59941:13"/>
                     <p>Place here the FIGURE Of the RULE</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="Gunter's line" type="treatise">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:59941:13"/>
            <head>
               <hi>THE</hi> Line of Proportion (or Numbers,) <hi>Commonly called Gunters Line;</hi> Made Eaſie.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hat this Line is, and how to make it, is beſt known to thoſe who make Mathematical In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruments; but the uſes of it are ſo general, that all ſorts of men, of what faculty ſoever, may apply it to his particular uſe, though it more immediately, and particularly, concerns ſuch Artificers whoſe em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ployment conſiſts in Menſtruation:
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:59941:14"/>as <hi>Carpenters, Joyners, Maſons, Bricklayers, Painters, Glaſiers,</hi> and ſuch like; for that all kind of menſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations, either <hi>SUPERFICIAL;</hi> as <hi>Board, Glaſs, Pavement, Tyleing, &amp;c.</hi> Or <hi>SOLID,</hi> as <hi>Timber, Stone, Pillars, Piramids, &amp;c.</hi> are by this Line, moſt eaſily, ſpeedily, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>actly performed: For, whatſoever thing, concerning meaſure, that may be performed by Arithmetick, this Line will do exactly, and much ſoon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; as by the working of the ſeveral Rules in Arithmetick, by this Line ſhall be plainly made appear.</p>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> NUMERATION upon the Line.</head>
               <p>BEfore I ſhew you how to number upon the Line, it will be ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to let you underſtand how the
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:59941:14"/>Line is divided and numbered, as al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo, what thoſe diviſions and numbers ſet to them upon the Ruler, do ſig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>difie.</p>
               <p>Know therefore, that the Line of numbers begins at the Figure One, and ſo proceeds ſucceſſively from I to 2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9. and then on farther, by 1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9.10. at the end of the line.</p>
               <p>The firſt 1. which ſtandeth at the beginning of the line, repreſenteth the <hi>One tenth part</hi> of any Unite or Intiger, as One tenth part of a Foot, One tenth part of a Yard, Ell, Perch, Mile, &amp;c. Or it may ſignifie One tenth of a Year, Moneth, Hour, &amp;c. Or the one tenth of a Pound, Shilling, or Penny, &amp;c. Or the one tenth part of any thing either in Number, Weight, Meaſure, Tine, or the like. The Figure 2. ſignifies two tenth parts of any thing. The figure 3. three tenth parts. The figure 4. four tenth
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:59941:15"/>parts, &amp;c. till you come to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond 1. which ſtandeth in the middle of the line, which 1. ſignifieth One whole Unite or Intiger, as One whole Foot, Yard, Perch, &amp;c.</p>
               <p>Now the other intermediate diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, thoſe which ſtand between the fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures 1 and 2 (which are in number ten) do repreſent (each of them) one hundred part of one Unite or Intiger; ſo the firſt diviſion beyond the figure 1, repreſents 11 hundred parts of the Intiget, the ſecond diviſion, 12 hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred parts of the Intiger, and ſo on; the figure 2 repreſenting 20 hundred parts of the Intiger, and the next di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſion beyond 2 is 21 hundred parts, and ſo on, till you come to the figure 1 in the middle of the line, which re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenteth one whole Intiger. The fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure 2 ſignifieth two whole Intigers; the figure 3, three whole Intigers, and ſo on, till you come to 10 at the end of the line, which ſignifieth ten whole
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:59941:15"/>Intigers: and the intermediate divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions, which ſtand between 1 and 2 in the middle of the line are (every of them) tenth parts of the Intiger. So the Rule contains 10 whole Inti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers, every of which is divided into 10 parts.</p>
               <p>But if upon the line you would count numbers of more places then two, (which are all numbers above 10) then the 1 which is at the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the line, muſt be accounted one Intiger; and the 1 in the middle of the line, ten Intigers; and the 10 at the end, will be 100 Intigers.</p>
               <p>But yet farther, if upon the Line you would expreſſe numbers of more places than three (which are all num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers above 100). Then the 1 at the beginning of the line, is to be accoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted ten Intigers, the 1 in the middle a hundred Intigers, and the 10 at the end of the line 1000 Intigers.</p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:59941:16"/>
               <p>And if you proceed yet farther; then the 1 at the beginning muſt be accounted for a hundred Intigers, that in the middle a thouſand, and the 10 at the end of the line for 10000, ten thouſand Intigers.</p>
               <p>In this manner you might proceed farther, by counting the firſt 1 for 1000, 10000, &amp;c. Intigers, but to four places is ſufficient, which by a Rule of a competent length (as of two Foot) any queſtion concerning meaſuring, may be by one exactly e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough performed.</p>
               <p>The Diviſions and Numbers on the line being thus explained, it reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth now to ſhew you how to find that point upon the line, which ſhall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſent any number propoſed, and that I ſhall ſhew you in theſe Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitions following, which may fitly be called.</p>
               <div n="numeration" type="part">
                  <head>NUMERATION.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="proposition">
                     <pb n="7" facs="tcp:59941:16"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>PROP. I.</hi> A whole number conſiſting of two, three, or four places, being given; to finde the point upon the Line, which repreſenteth the ſame:</head>
                     <p>NOTE, Let your number given be of how many places ſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver; for the firſt figure of your num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, you muſt take the ſame figure upon the Line: For the ſecond fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure in your number, take the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber thereof on the grand (or larger) intermediate diviſions on the Line: For the third figure in your number, take the number thereof on the ſmal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler intermediate diviſions on the line. And for your fourth figure, you muſt find its place by eſtimation.</p>
                     <p>Example I. <hi>Let it be required to finde the place of</hi> 15 <hi>upon the Line.</hi> For your firſt figure 1, count the 1 in
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:59941:17"/>the middle of the Line, then for the 5 which is your ſecond figure, count five of the grand (or larger) interme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate diviſions upon the line, and that point is the very place upon the line repreſenting 15.</p>
                     <p>
                        <note place="margin">Note, that every fifth of the grand intermediate di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſions, is drawn forth with a long<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er line then the reſt for caſe in counting.</note>Again, <hi>To finde the place upon the Line repreſenting</hi> 37. For your firſt figure 3, count the figure 3 up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the Line, then for the 7, count 7 of the intermediate diviſions, and that point is the place upon the Rule re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſenting 37.</p>
                     <p>Example 2. <hi>Let it be required to finde the place of</hi> 134 <hi>upon the line.</hi> For your firſt figure 1, count 1 upon the line; for your ſecond figure 3, count three of the grand diviſions; and for the third figure 4, count 4 of the ſmalleſt intermediate diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and that very point is the place
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:59941:17"/>upon the Line repreſenting 134.</p>
                     <p>Again, <hi>To finde the place repreſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting</hi> 308. For your firſt figure 3, count the 3 upon the Line; for your ſecond figure o (which is a Cipher) count none of the grand diviſions; but for your laſt figure 8, count 8 of the intermediate diviſions, and that point ſhall be the place upon the line repreſenting 308.</p>
                     <p>Example 3. <hi>Let it be required to finde the place of</hi> 1350. For your firſt figure 1, take 1 on the middle of the Line: For your ſecond figure 3, take the figure 3 upon the line upwards; for the 5, count five of the grand intermediate diviſions, and that is the place of 1350.</p>
                     <p>Again, <hi>To finde the place of</hi> 1626. For your firſt figure 1, count the 1 on the middle of the Line; for your ſecond figure 6, count the figure 6 upon the line upwards; then for your third figure 2, count two of the
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:59941:18"/>grand diviſions; and for your laſt fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure 6, eſtimate ſix tenth parts of the next grand diviſion (which is ſomething more then half the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, (becauſe 6 is more then half 10), and that is the point upon the line repreſenting 1626.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Note,</hi> By theſe Examples laſt men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned, you may perceive, that the figures 1.2.3.4.5.6.7.8.9. do ſometimes ſignify themſelves alone, ſometimes 10.20.30, &amp;c. ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times 100.200.300, &amp;c. as the work performed thereby ſhall require. The firſt figure of every number is alwaies that which is here ſet down, and the reſt of the figures are to be ſupplyed according as the nature of the Queſtion ſhall require.</p>
                     <p>And by this variation and change of the powers of theſe numbers, from 1 to 10, or 100 or 1000, any pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion either Arithmetial or Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrical may be wrought. One
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:59941:18"/>whereof I will inſert for your better exerciſe of numbring on the Rule; by the often practice whereof, you will find the work facile and delightful, which ſhall be this following.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="proposition">
                     <head>
                        <hi>PROP. 2.</hi> Having two numbers given, to finde as many more as, you pleaſe, which ſhall be in continual proportion one to the other, as the two numbers given were.</head>
                     <p>FOr the working of this propoſiti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, this is <hi>THE RULE.</hi> Place one Foot of the Compaſſes in the firſt given number on the line, and extend the other Foot to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond given number, then may you turn the Compaſſes from that ſecond number to a third, from that third to a fourth, from that fourth to a fifth, a ſixth, a ſeventh, &amp;c. towhat number of places you pleaſe.</p>
                     <pb n="12" facs="tcp:59941:19"/>
                     <p>Example 1. <hi>Let the two given num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers be</hi> 2 <hi>and</hi> 4. Place one Foot of your Compaſſes in 2, and extend the other Foot to 4, then that Foot which now ſtandeth in 2, being turned a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout, will reach from 4 to 8, and from 8 to 16, from 16 to 32, from 32 to 64, from 64 to 128.</p>
                     <p>But when your Compaſſes ſtand in 64, if you turn them about yet far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, they will fall beyond the end of the line, wherefore you muſt place one Foot in ſome other, 64 nearer the be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginning of the line, and then the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Foot will reach to 128, and from 128 to 256, and from 256 to 512, and from 512 to 1024, but here it will go off of your line again, where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of (as before) you muſt chooſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother 512 nearer the beginning of the line, and there placing you Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, they will reach to 1024. from 1024 to 2048, from 2048 to 4096, &amp;c.</p>
                     <pb n="13" facs="tcp:59941:19"/>
                     <p>Example 2. <hi>But if the given num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers were</hi> 10 <hi>and</hi> 9 <hi>decreaſing,</hi> then place one Foot in 10 at the end of line, and extend the other downwards to 9, the ſame extent will reach ſtill backwards to 8.1 (or 8 1/10) and from 8.1 to 7.29, and ſtill backwards from 7.29 to 6.56.</p>
                     <p>Likewiſe, if the two firſt numbers had been as 1 to 9, the third propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional would have been 81, the fourth 729, and the fifth 656, with the ſame extent of the Compaſſes.</p>
                     <p>Again:</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Let the two numbers be</hi> 10 <hi>and</hi> 12, place one Foot in 10, and extend the other to 12, that extent will reach from 12 to 14.4, and from thence to 17.28.</p>
                     <p>But if the numbers were 1 and 12, then the third proportional would be 144, and the fourth 1728, and all with the ſame extent of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="14" facs="tcp:59941:20"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> MULTIPLICATION by the Line.</head>
               <p>IN Multiplication, the Proportion is this:
<list>
                     <item>As 1 upon the Line, Is to one of the numbers to be multiplyed:</item>
                     <item>So is the other of the numbers to be multiplyed, To the Product of them. Which is the number ſought.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Example 1. <hi>Let it be required to multiply</hi> 5 <hi>by</hi> 7. The proportion is;</p>
               <p>As 1 ∶ to 5 ∷ ſo is 7 ∶ to 35.</p>
               <p>Therefore</p>
               <p>Set one Foot of your Compaſſes in 1, and extend the other Foot to 5; with that extent of the Compaſſes,
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:59941:20"/>place one Foot in 7, and the other Foot will fall upon 35, which is the Product.</p>
               <p>Example 2. <hi>Let it be required to multiply</hi> 32 <hi>by</hi> 9. The Proportion is;</p>
               <p>As 1 ∶ to 9 ∷ ſo 32 ∶ to 288.</p>
               <p>Set one Foot in one, and extend the other Foot to 9, that ſame extent will reach from 32 to 288, which is the product or ſum of 32, being mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiplyed by 9.</p>
               <p>Otherwiſe</p>
               <p>Set one Foot in 1, and extend the other to 32, the ſame extent will reach from 9, to 288, as before.</p>
               <p>Example 3. <hi>Let it be required to multiply</hi> 8 75/100 <hi>by</hi> 5 45/100. The Analogy or Proportion is;</p>
               <p>As 1 ∶ to 8.75 ∷ ſo 6.45 ∶ to 56.44. <hi>fere.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Set one Foot in 1, and extend the other to 8.75, the ſame extent ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed forward upon the line, will reach from 6.45 to 56.44. <hi>fere.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:59941:21"/>
               <p>Or if you ſet one Foot in 1, and extend the other to 6.45: The ſame extent will reach from 8.75 to 56.44, almoſt (namely to 43 ¾) as before.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> DIVISION by the Line.</head>
               <p>IN Diviſion three things are to be minded, <hi>viz.</hi>
               </p>
               <list>
                  <item>The Dividend, or number to be divided.</item>
                  <item>The Diviſor, the number by which the Dividend is divided.</item>
                  <item>The Quotient, which is the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſought.</item>
               </list>
               <p>And ſo often as the Diviſor is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in the Dividend, ſo often doth the Quotient contain Unity.</p>
               <p>For the working of Diviſion, this is the Analogy.</p>
               <pb n="17" facs="tcp:59941:21"/>
               <p>As the Diviſor is to Unity, or 1.</p>
               <p>So is the Dividend to the Quotient.</p>
               <p>Example 1. <hi>Let it be required to divide</hi> 35 <hi>by</hi> 7. The Proportion is;</p>
               <p>As 7 ∶ to 1 ∷ ſo 35 ∶ to 5.</p>
               <p>Set one Foot of the Compaſſes in 7, and extend the other Foot down<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards to one; that ſame extent will reach from 35 downwards to 5, which is the Quotient, and ſo many times is 7 contained in 35.</p>
               <p>Otherwiſe</p>
               <p>Extend the Compaſſes upwards from 7 to 35, that ſame extent will reach upwards from 1 to 5, as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p>Example 2. <hi>Let it be required to divide</hi> 288 <hi>by</hi> 32. The Proportion is;</p>
               <p>As 32 ∶ to 1 ∷ ſo 288 ∶ to 9.</p>
               <pb n="18" facs="tcp:59941:22"/>
               <p>Extend t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e Compaſſes downwards from 32 to 1, that ſame extent will reach downwards from 288 to 9, which is the Quotient.</p>
               <p>Or extend the Compaſſes upwards from 32 to 288; the ſame extent will reach upwards from 1 to 9. as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p>Example 3. <hi>Let it be required to divide</hi> 56.44 <hi>by</hi> 8.75. The Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is;</p>
               <p>As 8.75 ∶ to 1 ∷ ſo 56.44 ∶ to 6.45.</p>
               <p>Extend the Compaſſes downwards from 8.75 to 1, the ſame extent will reach downwards from 56.44 to 6.45.</p>
               <p>Or extend them upwards from 8.75, to 56.44, the ſame will reach upwards from 1 to 6.45. as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note</hi> this in Diviſion, That ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny times as the Diviſor may be orderly ſet under the Dividend in Arithmetical Work, ſo many
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:59941:22"/>places of figures ſhall be in the Quotient of your Diviſion: As if 34785 were to be divided by 75, the Quotient ſhall conſiſt of three figures only, namely of 463, becauſe 75 can be but three times ſet orderly under 34785 in Arithmetical operation.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IV.</hi> The GOLDEN-RULE Direct by the Line.</head>
               <p>THis Rule may well be termed the Golden-Rule, it being the moſt uſeful of all others; for having three numbers given you, may, by it, finde a fourth in proportion to them, as by divers Examples following ſhall be made plain. And this Rule is per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed upon the Line, with the like eaſe and exactneſs, as any of thoſe
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:59941:23"/>before mentioned: And for the working of it upon the Line, this is the general Analogy or Proportion.</p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>As the firſt number given, Is to the ſecond number given;</item>
                     <item>So is the third number given, To the fourth number required.</item>
                  </list>
Or
<list>
                     <item>As the firſt number given, Is to the third number given;</item>
                     <item>So is the ſecond number given, To the fourth number ſought.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore</p>
               <p>Alwaies, <hi>Extend the Compaſſes from the firſt number to the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, and that diſtance or extent applied, the ſame way, upon the Line, ſhall reach from the third, to the fourth number required.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Or otherwiſe, <hi>Extend the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes from the firſt number to the third, and that extent applyed the ſame way, ſhall alſo reach from the ſecond to the fourth.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="21" facs="tcp:59941:23"/>
               <p>Either of theſe waies will effect the ſame thing, as by Examples fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing ſhall be made appear.</p>
               <p>And it is neceſſary thus to vary the proportion, ſometimes, to avoid the opening of the Compaſſes too wide; for when the Compaſſes are opened to a very large extent, you can nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther take off any diſtance exactly, nor give ſo a good eſtimate of any parts required, as you may do when they are opened to a leſſer diſtance: But this you will find out beſt by practice; and therefore I will now proceed to Examples.</p>
               <p>Example 1. <hi>If</hi> 45 <hi>yards of Cloth coſt</hi> 30 <hi>pound, what will</hi> 84 <hi>yards coſt at the ſame rate?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As 45 ∶ to 38 ∷ ſo 84 ∶ to 56.</p>
               <p>Extend the Compaſſes downward from 45 to 30, that extent will reach downward from 84 to 56 <abbr>l.</abbr> the price of 84 yards.</p>
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:59941:24"/>
               <p>Or extend the Compaſſes upwards from 45 to 84, the ſame will reach from 30 to 56, as before.</p>
               <p>Example 2. <hi>If</hi> 26 <hi>Acres of Land be worth</hi> 64 <abbr>l.</abbr> 
                  <hi>a year; what is</hi> 36 <hi>Acres of the like Land worth by the year.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As 26 ∶ to 64 ∷ ſo 36 ∶ to 88.615.</p>
               <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 26 to 64, the ſame extent will reach from 36 to 88 615/1000 parts (which is about 12 <abbr>
                     <hi>s.</hi>
                  </abbr> 3 <abbr>
                     <hi>d.</hi>
                  </abbr> 2 <abbr>
                     <hi>q.</hi>
                  </abbr>) and ſo much is 36 Acres of the like Land worth by the year.</p>
               <p>Example 3. <hi>If</hi> 100 <hi>
                     <abbr>l.</abbr> yield</hi> 6 <hi>
                     <abbr>l.</abbr> Intereſt for one year, or</hi> 12 <hi>moneths, what ſhall</hi> 75 <hi>
                     <abbr>l.</abbr> yield?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>As 100 ∶ to 6 ∷ 75 ∶ to 4.50.</p>
               <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 100 to 6, the ſame extent will reach from 75. to 4.50. (or 4 ½) which is 4 <abbr>l.</abbr> 10 <abbr>
                     <hi>s</hi>
                  </abbr>, and ſo much will 75 <abbr>l.</abbr> yield in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tereſt in the year.</p>
               <p>Example 4. <hi>If</hi> 75 <hi>
                     <abbr>l.</abbr> yield</hi> 4 <abbr>
                     <hi>l.</hi>
                  </abbr> 10 <hi>
                     <abbr>s.</abbr> intereſt for one year, or</hi> 12 <hi>moneths, what will</hi> 100 <hi>
                     <abbr>l.</abbr> yield?</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="23" facs="tcp:59941:24"/>
               <p>As 75 ∶ to 4.50 ∷ ſo 160 ∶ to 67.</p>
               <p>Extend the Compaſſes downwards from 75 to 4.50, the ſame extent will reach from 100 to 6, and ſuch inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſt will 100 <abbr>l.</abbr> yield.</p>
               <p>Many other Queſtions might be added, but the Rule (and man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of working it) is ſo plain, that it needs them not, and ſo general, that he which can re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolve one, may as well reſolve any other, and therefore I ſhall ſay no more of it in this place.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. V.</hi> The GOLDEN-RULE Reverſe by the Line.</head>
               <p>IN this reverſe or backward Rule of Three, this note is ſpecially to be obſerved, That if the third num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber be greater then the firſt, then will
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:59941:25"/>the fourth number be leſs then the ſecond. And on the contrary, if the third number be leſs than the firſt, then the fourth number will be greater than the ſecond. As by Examples will appear,</p>
               <p>Example 1. <hi>If</hi> 12 <hi>Workmen, do any piece of Work in</hi> 8 <hi>daies, how many Workmen ſhall do the ſame piece of Work in</hi> 2 <hi>daies?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>It is here to be noted, That in this Queſtion 12 is not the firſt num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber (though it be firſt named) but 2; for the middlemoſt terme of the three muſt be of the ſame kind with the fourth num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber which is to be ſought; as in this Example it is Men, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore 12 (which are men) muſt ſtand in the middle, or ſecond place, becauſe the fourth num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber which is to be ſought is alſo Men: And therefore the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers will ſtand thus,</p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:59941:25"/>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">dayes</cell>
                        <cell role="label">men</cell>
                        <cell role="label">dayes</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2,</cell>
                        <cell>12,</cell>
                        <cell>8.</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <p>For if 8 daies, require 12 men, then 2 daies (which is but a fourth part of 8 daies) ſhall require four time 12 men, that is, 48 men.</p>
               <p>For here, Leſs requires More; that is, leſs Time, more Hands, and hence the Work is contrary to the direct Rule: Wherefore to effect it,</p>
               <p>Extend the Compaſſes, from 2 to 8, the ſame extent will reach from 12 (the contrary way on the Line) to 48, which is the number of men that will effect the ſame piece of work in two daies.</p>
               <p>Example 2. <hi>If one Cloſe will graze</hi> 21 <hi>Horſes for</hi> 6 <hi>weeks, how many Hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes will the ſame Cloſe graze for</hi> 7 <hi>weeks?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 6 to 7, (for you muſt alwaies extend your Compaſſes to numbers of one kind, or denomination, as here 6 and 7 are
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:59941:26"/>both Horſes) the ſame extent will reach from 21 backward to 18, and ſo many Horſes will the ſame Cloſe graze for 7 weeks.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VI.</hi> Of DUPLICATE PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PORTION by the Line.</head>
               <p>DUplicate proportion is ſuch a proportion as is between Lines and Superficies, or between Super<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficies and Lines.</p>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <head>1. <hi>Of the proportion of LINES to SUPERFICIES.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>In this Caſe, extend the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes from the firſt to the ſecond number of the ſame denomination, that ſame extent (being doubled) ſhall give the diſtance from the third number unto the fourth.</p>
                  <pb n="27" facs="tcp:59941:26"/>
                  <p>Example 1. <hi>If the Diameter of a Circle be</hi> 14 <hi>Inches, and the Area, or content thereof be</hi> 154 <hi>Inches, what will be the content of another Circle, whoſe Diameter is</hi> 28 <hi>Inches?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 14 to 28, that extent doubled, will reach from 154, to 616; for firſt it will reach from 154 to 308, and from thence to 616, and that is the Area or Content of a Circle whoſe Diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter is 28.</p>
                  <p>Example 2. <hi>If a piece of Land that is</hi> 20 <hi>Pole ſquare, be worth</hi> 30 <hi>pounds; what is a piece of Land of the ſame goodneſs worth that is</hi> 35 <hi>Pole ſquare.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 20 to 35, that extent doubled, will reach from 30 to 91.8, that is, 91 pound 8/10 of a pound, which is 16 ſhillings, and ſo much is ſuch a piece of Land worth.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:59941:27"/>
                  <head>II. <hi>Of the Proportion of SUPER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>FICIES to LINES.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>In this Caſe, Extend the Compaſſes unto the half of the diſtance between the two numbers of the ſame deno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mination; that ſame extent ſhall reach from the third number, to the fourth required.</p>
                  <p>Example 1. <hi>Let there be two Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles given, the Area or Content of the one being</hi> 154, <hi>and its Diameter</hi> 14 <hi>The Area of the other Circle is</hi> 616, <hi>what is the length of its Diameter?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Upon your Line, divide the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance between 154 and 616, into two equal parts, then with that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance ſet one Foot in 14, and the other ſhall fall upon 28, which is the length of the Diameter of the other Circle, whoſe Area is 616.</p>
                  <p>Example 2. <hi>There is a piece of Land containing</hi> 20 <hi>Pole ſquare worth</hi> 30 <hi>pound, there is another piece worth</hi> 91 <hi>pound</hi> 16 <abbr>
                        <hi>s.</hi>
                     </abbr> 
                     <hi>how many Pole ſquare
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:59941:27"/>ought that piece to contain?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Take with your Compaſſes halfe the diſtance between 30 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> and 91 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> 16 <abbr>s.</abbr> Then ſet one foot in 20 pole, and the other foot will reach to 35 Pole, and ſo many Pole ſquare muſt the Land be that is worth 91 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> 16 <abbr>s.</abbr>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VII.</hi> OF TRIPLICATE PRO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>POTION by the Line.</head>
               <p>TRiplicate proportion is ſuch a proportion as is between <hi>Lines</hi> and <hi>Solids,</hi> or between <hi>Solids</hi> and <hi>Lines.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <head>1. <hi>Of the Proportion between LINES and SOLIDS</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>In this Caſe, Extend the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes from the firſt number to the ſecond of the ſame denomination,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:59941:28"/>that extent (being tripled) ſhall reach from the third number to the f<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>rth.</p>
                  <p>Example. <hi>There is a Bullet whoſe Diameter is</hi> 4 <hi>Inches, weying</hi> 9 <abbr>
                        <hi>l.</hi>
                     </abbr> 
                     <hi>What ſhall another bullet of the ſame mettall weigh, whoſe Diameter ſhall be</hi> 8 <hi>inches.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 4 to 8 (the two Diameters) the ſame extent (being tripled) will reach from 9 to 72. which is the weight of a bullet whoſe diameter is 8 in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II. <hi>Of the proportion of SOLIDS to LINES.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>In this Caſe Extend the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes unto the third part of the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance between the two numbers of like denomination, that ſame extent ſhall reach from the third to the fourth number required.</p>
                  <p>Example. <hi>The weight of a Cube being</hi> 72 <hi>pound, the Side whereof was</hi>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:59941:28"/>8 <hi>inches; and the weight of another Cube of the ſame matter weighting</hi> 9 <hi>pound, what muſt the ſide be?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Upon your line divide the diſtance between 9 and 72 into three equal parts, then ſet one foot of that diſtance in 8, and the other foot ſhall reſt in 4, the length of the ſide of the Cube required.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. VIII.</hi> The Extraction of the SQARE-ROOT By the Line.</head>
               <p>TO Extract the Square-Root, is to find a mean proportional Number between 1 and the number given, and therefore is to be found by dividing the ſpace between them into two equal parts.</p>
               <pb n="32" facs="tcp:59941:29"/>
               <p>Example. <hi>Let it be required to find the Square-Root of</hi> 36.</p>
               <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 1 to 36, the middle way upon the Line between theſe two numbers is 6, which is the Square-Root of 36. In like manner may you find the Square-Root of 81 to be 9, of 144 to be 12, of 256 to be 16; and of other numbers as in this Table.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Root.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Square.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Root.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Square.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>121</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>144</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>169</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>196</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>25</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>225</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>36</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>256</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>49</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>289</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>64</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>324</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>81</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>361</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>100</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>400</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
               <pb n="33" facs="tcp:59941:29"/>
               <p>If you ſuppoſe the number to have pricks over every ſecond Figure, as is uſual in the Arithmetical Operation, then if the laſt prick towards the left hand fall over the laſt Figure (which will always be when the number of Figures are odde) then it will be beſt to place Unity at the 1 in the middle of the line, ſo that the Root and the Square may both fall forward towards 10 at the end of the Line.</p>
               <p>But if the number of Figures be even, it will then be beſt to place Unity at 10 at the end of the Line; ſo the Root and the Square both will fall backwards towards the middle of the Line.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <pb n="34" facs="tcp:59941:30"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. IX.</hi> The Extraction of the C<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BE-ROOT By the Line.</head>
               <p>TO Extract the Cube-Root, is to find the firſt of two mean pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portionals between 1 and the number whoſe Cube-Root you require, and is therefore to be found upon the Line, by dividing the ſpace between them into three equal parts.</p>
               <p>Example. <hi>Let it be required to find the Cube-Root of</hi> 216.</p>
               <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 1 to 216, one third part of that diſtance ſhall reach from one to 6, which is the Cube-Root of 216. In like manner
<pb n="35" facs="tcp:59941:30"/>may you find the Cube-Root of 729 to be 9, of 1728 to be 12, of 110592 to be 48, of 493039 to be 79, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as in this Table.</p>
               <p>
                  <table>
                     <row>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Root.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Cube.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Root.</hi>
                        </cell>
                        <cell role="label">
                           <hi>Cube.</hi>
                        </cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>1</cell>
                        <cell>11</cell>
                        <cell>1331</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>2</cell>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>12</cell>
                        <cell>1728</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>3</cell>
                        <cell>27</cell>
                        <cell>13</cell>
                        <cell>2197</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>4</cell>
                        <cell>64</cell>
                        <cell>14</cell>
                        <cell>2744</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>5</cell>
                        <cell>125</cell>
                        <cell>15</cell>
                        <cell>3375</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>6</cell>
                        <cell>216</cell>
                        <cell>16</cell>
                        <cell>4096</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>7</cell>
                        <cell>343</cell>
                        <cell>17</cell>
                        <cell>4913</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>8</cell>
                        <cell>512</cell>
                        <cell>18</cell>
                        <cell>5832</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>9</cell>
                        <cell>729</cell>
                        <cell>19</cell>
                        <cell>6859</cell>
                     </row>
                     <row>
                        <cell>10</cell>
                        <cell>1000</cell>
                        <cell>20</cell>
                        <cell>8000</cell>
                     </row>
                  </table>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="10" type="chapter">
               <pb n="36" facs="tcp:59941:31"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. X.</hi> The Uſe of the Line, applied to SUPERFICIAL-MEASURE, Such as Board, Glaſs, Wainſcot, Pavement, Hangings, Paintings, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> of what kind ſoever.</head>
               <p>THe Meaſures by which Board, Glaſs, Timber, Stone, and ſuch like are meaſured, is by the Foot, a Foot containing 12 Inches, and each Inch into eight parts called halves, quarters, and half-quarters; but this kind of diviſion not being conſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous or agreeable to the diviſions upon your Line of Proportion, where between 1 and 2 is divided (not into 8, but) into 10 parts, the like be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 2 and 3 into 10 parts, and ſo between 3 and 4,4 and 5, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> There<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore,
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:59941:31"/>I hold it requiſite both for eaſe and exactneſs, to have every Inch on your two-foot Rule divided not into 8, but into 10 equal parts, which here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after (throughout this Book) we will call Inch-Meaſure.</p>
               <p>Again, Whereas your Foot is di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into 12 equal parts called In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, I would have your Foot divided into 10 equal parts, and each of thoſe parts ſub-divided into 10 other equal parts, ſo will you whole Foot contain 100 equal parts, which will be agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able to the diviſions of your Line, and facilitate the work, as by the Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples in this kind given will be made to appear; and this we ſhall hereafter call Foot-Meaſure.</p>
               <p>But if any perſon be ſo wedded to Inches halves and quarters, that he will not be beaten out of his opinion, but perſiſt therein, and yet is deſirous to have knowledge in the uſe of this Line, I ſay, ſuch perſon may have ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:59941:32"/>to the ſide of his Inches halves and quarters (by way of faceing, as I term it) a line of Foot-meaſure, and alſo his Inches into 10 as well as 8, ſo that he may meaſure by one, and work upon his Line by the other. And this indeed will be neceſſary to be done upon the Rules of thoſe ingeni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Artificers who need them not, for that they many times meet with wilful perſons that will have them to meaſure their way, how diſconſenta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neous to Reaſon ſoever it be.</p>
               <p>In this nature would I have the Rule divided, and in this manner have I cauſed them to be made both for my ſelf and others, a figure whereof I have inſerted at the beginning of the Book.</p>
               <p>And here note, That what is here ſaid concerning dividing the Inch and Foot into 10 parts, the like is to be underſtood of the Yard, Ell, Pole or Perch,
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:59941:32"/>or any other meaſure whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever.</p>
               <p>Theſe things being premiſed, we will now proceed to Examples.</p>
               <div n="1" type="examples">
                  <head>I. <hi>Examples in Inch-Meaſure only.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Example 1. <hi>Let a Board or Plank be</hi> 37 <hi>Inches broad, and</hi> 263 <hi>Inches long, how many Square Inches is there in ſuch a Plank?</hi> The Proportion is,
<list>
                        <item>As 1, is to 27, the breadth in Inches;</item>
                        <item>So is 263, the length in Inches, To 7101, the number of Square Inches in the whole Plank.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 1 to 27, the ſame extent forwards, will reach from 263, to 7101 the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent.</p>
                  <p>Or, you may extend the Compaſſes
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:59941:33"/>from 1 to 263, the ſame will reach from 27 to 7101, as before.</p>
                  <p>Example 2. <hi>Let a Pain of Glaſs be</hi> 53.4 <hi>Inches broad, and</hi> 126.8 <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches long; how many Foot is there in that Pain?</hi> The Proportion is,</p>
                  <p>As 144 (becauſe 144 Inches make 1 Foot) is to 53.4, the breadth in Inches;</p>
                  <p>So is 126.8, the length in Inches, to 47.06 the content in Feet.</p>
                  <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 144 to 53.4, the ſame will reach from 126.8, to 47.06, which is 47 Foot and <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 6/9 parts of a Foot, the content of the whole Pain.</p>
                  <p>Example 3. <hi>If a Marble Foot-pace or Walk be</hi> 20 <hi>Inches broad, how much in length of that will make a Foot, ſquare</hi> 3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> The proportion is,
<list>
                        <item>As 20, the breadth in Inches,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:59941:33"/>
is to 144, the Inches in one Foot;</item>
                        <item>So is 1 Foot, unto the length of one Foot in Inch-meaſure.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 20 to 144, that extent will reach from 1 to 7.2; ſo that 7 Inches and 2/10 of that breadth will make a Foot ſquare.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="examples">
                  <head>II. <hi>Examples in Foot-Meaſure only.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Example 1. <hi>Let a Floor or Stone-pavement be</hi> 52 <hi>Foot broad, and</hi> 1105 <hi>Foot long, how many Foot ſquare in that Floor or Pavement?</hi> The Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion is.
<list>
                        <item>As 1 Foot, to 52 Foot the breadth;</item>
                        <item>So 100.5 Foot the length, to 5746 the content in ſquare Feet.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 1 to
<pb n="42" facs="tcp:59941:34"/>52, the ſame will reach from 110.5, to 5746, the content of the Pavement or Floor in ſquare Feet.</p>
                  <p>Example 2. <hi>There is a Plank of Cedar</hi> 2 <hi>Foot</hi> 25 <hi>parts broad; how much in length thereof will make a Foot ſquare?</hi> The Proportion is,
<list>
                        <item>As 2.25 the breadth, is to 1;</item>
                        <item>So is 1, or any number of Feet, to the length of a Foot ſquare in Foot-meaſure.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 2.25 to 1, that extent will reach back from 100, which is one Foot, to 44 parts; and ſo many parts in length of that Plank will make a Foot. In like manner 88 parts will make 2 Foot, 1 Foot 32 parts will make 3 Foot, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For,
<list>
                        <item>As 2.25, is to 1 Foot;</item>
                        <pb n="43" facs="tcp:59941:34"/>
                        <item>So is 
<list>
                              <head>parts.</head>
                              <item>100</item>
                              <item>200</item>
                              <item>300</item>
                           </list>
to
<list>
                              <head>parts.</head>
                              <item>44</item>
                              <item>88</item>
                              <item>132, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                              </item>
                           </list>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">III. <hi>Examples in Inch-Meaſure and Foot-Meaſure together.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Example 1. <hi>Let a Board be</hi> 30 <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches broad, and</hi> 15 <hi>Foot and</hi> ¼ <hi>or</hi> 25 <hi>parts long; how many Foot ſquare d<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>th ſuch a Board or Plank contain?</hi> The Analogy is,
<list>
                        <item>As 12 Inches, to 30 the breadth in Inches;</item>
                        <item>So 15.25 the length in Feet, to 38.125 the content in Feet.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 12 to 30, the ſame will reach from 15.25 to 38.125; and ſo many Foot ſquare is contained in ſuch a Plank.</p>
                  <p>I will conclude this Chapter with
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59941:35"/>this uſeful and neceſſary <hi>Problem,</hi> Namely,</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>By having the length and breadth of any Long Square, or Parallelogram, to finde the length of a ſide of a Geo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>metrical Square equal thereunto.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <note place="margin">Note, By a Long Square or Paral<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lelogram is meant any Square whoſe ſides are longer one than another, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny lo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>g Table, &amp;c. But a Geometrical Square is that whoſe <hi>4</hi> ſides are all of one length.</note>This by the Line is eaſily effected; for if you take the half-diſtance upon your Line between the length and the breadth, the Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber upon which the Compaſs point reſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, ſhall be, the length of the ſide of the Geometrical Square, equal to the Long Square or Parallelogram.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Example.</hi> Let the longer ſide of a Parallelogram be 183 Inches, and the breadth 30 Inches: If you divide the diſtance upon your Line between
<pb n="45" facs="tcp:59941:35"/>theſe two Numbers into two equal parts, the Compaſs point ſhall-reſt upon 74 Inches 10 parts: So that a Geometrical Square whoſe ſide is 74.10, ſhall be equal in Area to a Long Square whoſe ſides are 30 and 183.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="11" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XI.</hi> OF YARD-MEAS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE By the Line.</head>
               <p>MAny Artificers, as Joyners, Painters, Plaiſterers, Pavi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, Upholſters, meaſure and ſell their Work, not by the Foot but by the Yard, it will be neceſſary to give Examples in this kind of Meaſure al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo. And here alſo it is requiſite that your Yard be divided into 100 parts,
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:59941:36"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:59941:36"/>
                  <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                     <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <pb n="46" facs="tcp:59941:37"/>and not into Halves, Quarters, and Nails; which ſuppoſed, take theſe Examples following.</p>
               <p>Example 1. <hi>A Joyner hath Wainſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>coted a Gallery containing</hi> 130 <hi>Yards</hi> 25 <hi>parts about, and in height</hi> 15 <hi>Yards</hi> 50 <hi>parts; how many ſquare Yards is in that Gallery?</hi> The proportion is,
<list>
                     <item>As 1 yard, to 15.50 yards the height;</item>
                     <item>So 130.25 the compaſs in yards, 10 2018.87 the content in yards,</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 1 to 15.50 the breadth, the ſame extent will reach from 130.25 the length, to 2018.87; and ſo many Square Yards of Wainſcoting is in that Gallery.</p>
               <p>Example 2. <hi>A Painter hath paint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Landskip, or other Work, over the Wainſcot of a Room, which is</hi> 1 <hi>Yard</hi> 75 <hi>parts of a Yard deep; how much
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:59941:37"/>in length thereof will make a Yard Square?</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>As the breadth 1.75, is to 1 yard or 100 parts;</item>
                     <item>So is 1, or any other numb. of yards, to the length of a yard ſquare.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 1 to 1.75, the ſame extent will reach from 100 (or one yard) to 75.14; and ſo much in length of that painting will make a yard ſquare.</p>
               <p>Example 3. <hi>A Plaiſterer hath laid and beautified a Cieling containing</hi> 13 <hi>yards broad, and</hi> 63 <hi>yards</hi> 30 <hi>parts long; how many ſquare yards is there in that Cieling?</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>As 1 yard, to the breadth 13 yards;</item>
                     <item>So the length 63.30, to the content.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 1 to
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:59941:38"/>13, the ſame extent will reach from 63.30, to 823 almoſt; and ſo many ſquare yards are there in ſuch a Ciel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Note,</hi> It may ſo fall out ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times, that it will be required to meaſure ſome piece of Work, and to give an eſtimate of the quantity of the yards therein contained, when you have not a yard thus divided by you, but only your two-foot Rule; for the ſupplying whereof I will add this following Problem.</p>
               <div type="problem">
                  <head>PROBLEM. The length and breadth of any Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficies being given in Feet, in finde the content thereof in Yards.</head>
                  <p>Let the breadth of a piece of any Work, to be paid for by the Yard, be 4 Foot, and the Length thereof 12 Foot,
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:59941:38"/>how many ſquare Yards are contained therein?</p>
                  <p>The Analogy or Proportion is,
<list>
                        <item>As 9, is to 4, the breadth in Feet;</item>
                        <item>So is 12, the length. to 5 36/100 the content in yards.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 9 to 4, the ſame extent will reach (the ſame way) from 12 to 5.35, that is, to 5 yards, and 35 hundred parts of a yard, which is 35 yards, one quarter, and almoſt half a quarter of a yard.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="12" type="chapter">
               <pb n="50" facs="tcp:59941:39"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XII.</hi> OF LAND-MEAS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE By the Line.</head>
               <p>THe uſual Meaſures for Land are Chains, of which there are di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vers ſorts; but the denominations of the quantity of Land is given in in Acres and Perches.</p>
               <p>The Chains now moſt in uſe are principally two;</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <list>
                        <item>One containing 1 Perch in length,</item>
                        <item>The other 4 Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches in length,</item>
                     </list> each of them di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into 100 links.</item>
               </list>
               <p>For the practice of them take theſe Examples.</p>
               <pb n="51" facs="tcp:59941:39"/>
               <p n="1">I. <hi>By the</hi> 1 <hi>Pole Chain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Example 1. <hi>There is a plat of ground</hi> 30 <hi>Perches broad, and</hi> 183 <hi>Perches long; how many Perches doth it contain?</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>As 1, to 30 the breadth;</item>
                     <item>So 183 the length, to 5490 the content.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 1 to 30, that ſhall reach from 183 to 5490 the content.</p>
               <p>Example 2. <hi>But the length and breadth of the ſame piece of ground being given as before in Perches, if it were required to find the content in Acres,</hi> then,
<list>
                     <item>As 160, to 30 the breadth;</item>
                     <pb n="50" facs="tcp:59941:40"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="51" facs="tcp:59941:40"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="52" facs="tcp:59941:41"/>
                     <item>So 183, to 34 Acres 31/100 parts of an Acre.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 160 to 30, the ſame ſhall reach (being ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended the ſame way) from 183 to 34.31, that is, 34 Acres, 31 hundred parts of an Acre, which is ſomething above a Rood.</p>
               <p n="2">II. <hi>By the Four Pole Chain.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Example 1. <hi>A piece of Land con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining</hi> 16 <hi>Chains</hi> 25 <hi>Links in breadth, and</hi> 57 <hi>Chains</hi> 30 <hi>Links in length, how many Acres doth it con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain?</hi> The Analogy is,
<list>
                     <item>As 10, to 16.25 the breadth in Chains and Links;</item>
                     <item>So is 57.30 the length in Chains and Links, to 93 Acres 925/10060 parts of an Acre.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <pb n="53" facs="tcp:59941:41"/>
               <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 10 to 16.25, the ſame extent will reach from 57.30, to 93.0925.</p>
               <p>Example 2. <hi>The Baſe and Perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicular of a Triangle being given in Chains and Links, to finde the content in Acres.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>This is a right uſeful and neceſſary Propoſition; for by it all manner of irregular plats of Land are caſt up: But my intent here is not to teach Surveying, but to ſhew the uſe of the Line of Proportion.</p>
               <p>Wherefore, Let the Perpendicu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar of the Triangle be 7 Chains 50 Links, and the Baſe 45 Chains 75 Links, the proportion will be,
<list>
                     <item>As 20, to 7.50 the Perpendicular;</item>
                     <item>So is 45.75 the Baſe, to 17.15 the content.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 20 to
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:59941:42"/>7.50, that extent ſhall reach from 45.75 to 17.15, which is 17. Acres, and 15/100 parts.</p>
               <p>Example 3. <hi>Having the length of any Furlong given, to finde what breadth it muſt have to make an Acre.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let the length of the Furlong be 12 Chains 50 Links, then to finde the breadth for one Acre this is the Analogy.
<list>
                     <item>As 15.20 the length in Chains, is unto 10;</item>
                     <item>So is 1 Acre, to 80 Links, which muſt be the breadth of the Furlong.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore,</p>
               <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 10 to 12.50, the ſame will reach from 1 A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cre to 80 Links the breadth of the Furlong.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="13" type="chapter">
               <pb n="55" facs="tcp:59941:42"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIII.</hi> Of the Menſuration of divers Regular SUPERFICIAL-FIG<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RES by the Line.</head>
               <p>HAving ſufficiently ſhewn the manner of meaſuring of ſuch Superficial-Figures as are meaſured by length and breadth, I will now ſhew you how by the Line to meaſure ſome other Regular Figures, as ahe Circle, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <head>I. <hi>Of the</hi> Circle.</head>
                  <p>Example 1. <hi>The length of the dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter of any Circle being given, to finde the Circumference thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The proportion between the dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:59941:43"/>and the circumference of any Circle is as 7 to 22; or, in exacter terms, as 1000 to 3140.</p>
                  <p>Wherefore,</p>
                  <p>If the diameter of a Circle given be 23 Inches, the circumference therefore may be found by this fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Analogy.
<list>
                        <item>As 1.000, is to 3.140;</item>
                        <item>So is 12 the diameter, to 37.68 the Circumference.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherefore extend the Compaſſes from 1.000, to 3.140, the ſame ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent ſhall reach from 12, to 37 In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches 68 parts, which is the Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence.</p>
                  <p>Example 2. <hi>The circumference of any Circle being given, to finde the length of the diameter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is the converſe of the former Example, and the Analogy is the converſe alſo.</p>
                  <pb n="57" facs="tcp:59941:43"/>
                  <p>Let the circumference of a Circle be 37 Inches 68 parts, what is the length of the diameter?
<list>
                        <item>As 3.140, to 1.000;</item>
                        <item>So is 37 Inches 68 parts the cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference, to 12 Inches the diameter.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 3.140, to 1.000, the ſame extent will reach from 37.68, to 12, the diameter re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.</p>
                  <p>Example 3. <hi>Having the diameter of a Circle, to finde the length of the ſide of a Square, which ſhall be equal in content to the ſame Circle.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If the diameter of a Circle be 12 Inches, the proportion is,
<list>
                        <item>As 1.0000, is to 12 Inches the diameter,</item>
                        <item>So is 8862, to 10.63 the ſide of the Square.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="58" facs="tcp:59941:44"/>
                  <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 10000 to 12, the ſame extent will reach from 8862, to 10 Inches 63 hundred parts, the ſide of a Square equal in Area to the Circle whoſe diameter is 12 Inches.</p>
                  <p>Eample 4. <hi>Having the Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of a Circle given, to finde the ſide of a Square equal to that Circle.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let the circumference of the gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven Circle be 37 Inches 68 parts; The proportion is,
<list>
                        <item>As 10000, to 37.68 the circumference;</item>
                        <item>So is 2832, to 10.63 the ſide of the Square.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 10000 to 37.68, the ſame will reach from 2821, to 10 Inches 63 parts, the ſide of the Square required.</p>
                  <p>Example 5. <hi>The diameter of a
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:59941:44"/>Circle being given, to finde the ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficial content thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let the diameter of a Circle be 15 Inches.</p>
                  <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 1 to 15 the diameter, then apply one foot of that diſtance (alwaies) to 7854; then turn that diſtance twice from this number the ſame way, and the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſs point will fall upon 176 Inches 74 parts, which is the Area of that Circle whoſe diameter is 15 Inches.</p>
                  <p>Example 6. <hi>The circumference of a Circle being given, to finde the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let the circumference of a Circle given be 47 Inches 13 parts.</p>
                  <p>Exetnd the Compaſſes from 1 to 47.13 the Circumference; this di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance being applied (alwaies) to this number 7958, and from thence twice repeated, the point of the Compaſſes at the ſecond remove will fall upon
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:59941:45"/>176 Inches 74 parts, equal to the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rea of the Circle as before.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note.</hi> Here note, That your Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes being opened from 1 to 47.13 the Circumference, when you come to ſet one foot upon 7958, the other will reach at your firſt turning over to 37.8; and when you turn them over again it will fall out of the line; wherefore you muſt ſet one foot in 37.8 in the lower part of the Line, and then the other will fall upon 176.74. And thus you muſt do in other caſes, whenever your Compaſs point goes beyond your Line.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="14" type="chapter">
               <pb n="61" facs="tcp:59941:45"/>
               <head>CHAP. XIV. II. <hi>Of the</hi> Triangle.</head>
               <p>A Triangle is a Figure conſiſting of three ſides and three angles, the longeſt ſide whereof we call the baſe; and a line drawn from the Angle op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſite to the baſe we call the perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicular.</p>
               <p>To meaſure Triangles there are ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral ways; I will only ſhew you one or two to be done by the Line.</p>
               <p>Example 1. <hi>There is a Triangle whoſe baſe is</hi> 14 <hi>foot, and his perpen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicular</hi> 6 <hi>foot, I would know how many ſquare Foot is contained in this Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>angle.</hi> The proportion is,
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:59941:46"/>
                  <list>
                     <item>As 2, is to 6 the perpendicular;</item>
                     <item>So is 14 the baſe, to 42 the Area.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Or,
<list>
                     <item>As 1, is to 3, half the baſe;</item>
                     <item>So is 14, to 42 the Area.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Or,
<list>
                     <item>As 2, is to 6 the perpendicular;</item>
                     <item>So is 7 half the baſe, to 42 the Area.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Or,
<list>
                     <item>As 1, is to 6 the perpendicular;</item>
                     <item>So is 14 the baſe, to 84 the double Area.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>All theſe ways produce the ſame effect, but the firſt is the beſt:</p>
               <pb n="63" facs="tcp:59941:46"/>
               <p>Wherefore,</p>
               <p>The baſe of your Triangle being 14, and the perpendicular 6; Extend the Compaſſes from 2 to 6, the ſame extent will reach from 14, to 42 the Area.</p>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III. <hi>Of the</hi> Trapezia.</head>
                  <p>A <hi>Trapezia</hi> is any right lined fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure conſiſting of four unequal ſides and as many angles: For the meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring of it, you muſt firſt reduce it in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to two Triangles, by drawing a line or diameter from one oppoſite angle to another the longeſt way, then from the two angles oppoſite to this line, let fall two perpendiculars; ſo is the <hi>Trapezia</hi> divided into two Triangles. The manner how to meaſure it is this.</p>
                  <p>Example. <hi>There is a</hi> Trapezia <hi>whoſe diameter is</hi> 12.34, <hi>and one per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendicular
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:59941:47"/>is</hi> 4.20, <hi>the other</hi> 5.07; <hi>I would know the Content or Area there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The two perpendiculars added to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether make 9.27. Then the analogy is,
<list>
                        <item>As 2, is to 9.27, the ſum of the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dendiculars;</item>
                        <item>So is 12.34, the baſe, to 57.19, the Area.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>There are as many ways to meaſure Trapezias, as in the laſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample I gave you for Trian<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gles; but this is the beſt.</p>
                  <p>And here note, That if you are to meaſure any irregular piece, of what nature ſoever, whether Land, Board, Glaſs, Pavement, or the like, your beſt and exacteſt way is to reduce them to Trapezias, and meaſure them as before is taught.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <pb n="65" facs="tcp:59941:47"/>
                  <head>IIII. <hi>Of Regular Figures of</hi> 5, 6, 8, 10, <hi>or</hi> 20 <hi>equal ſides.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Theſe Figures by Geometricians are called Regular Polygons, and the way to meaſure them is by adding all the ſider together. Then meaſure the length from the centre of the figure to the middle of one of the ſides; by the help of theſe two you may finde the Area of the Figure.</p>
                  <p>Example. <hi>Let there be a Regular Polygon of</hi> 11 <hi>equal ſides, each ſide being</hi> 7 <hi>Inches; and let the length of the line from the centre to the middle of one of thoſe ſides be</hi> 12 <hi>Inches.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Add all the ſides together they make 77; then,
<list>
                        <item>As 2, is to 77 the ſum of the ſides;</item>
                        <item>So is 12, the length of the line from the middle of the figure, to 462, the content of the figure.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="15" type="chapter">
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:59941:48"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XV.</hi> The Uſe of the Line applied to SOLID-MEAS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RE Such as Timber, Stone, &amp;c.</head>
               <p>TImber and Stone are uſually mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured by the ſame Rule or Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure as Board and Glaſs are, namely, by Feet and Inches: Therefore ſuch a Rule as was mentioned in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the Tenth Chapter is fit for this buſineſs alſo.</p>
               <p>Before we come to ſhew the way of meaſuring of Stone or Timber, it will be neceſſary to premiſe thus much, That the baſe or end of every piece of Timber or Stone is (or muſt be ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed)
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:59941:48"/>either exactly ſquare, that is, eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſide alike, or elſe one of the ſides longer than the other: wherefore the firſt thing to be done is to finde the Area, or ſuperficial content of the baſe or end of any piece of Timber or Stone to be meaſured, which may be done ſeveral ways, either in Inch-Meaſure, as by the firſt Example of the firſt part of the tenth Chapter; or in Foot-Meaſure, by the firſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample in the ſecond part of the ſame Chapter; or both in Foot-meaſure and Inch-meaſure, as in the firſt Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ample of the third part of the ſame tenth Chapter; and therefore need not be here repeated again: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, we will proceed to our intended purpoſe of Meaſuring, firſt, by Inch-meaſure only; ſecondly, by Foot-meaſure only; and thirdly, by both together; as we did before in the meaſuring of Board, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:59941:49"/>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>1. <hi>In Inch-Meaſure only.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Example 1. <hi>There is a piece of Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> 30 <hi>Inches broad,</hi> 21 <hi>Inches</hi> 6 <hi>parts deep, and</hi> 183 <hi>Inches long; how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſquare Inches is there in this ſolid piece of Timber?</hi> The proportion is,</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <list>
                        <item>1. As 1, unto 30 Inches the breadth;</item>
                        <item>So is 21.6 Inches the depth, to 648 Inches, the content of the baſe of the piece.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <list>
                        <item>2. As 1, unto 648, the content of the baſe;</item>
                        <item>So is 183 Inches, the length of the piece, to 118584, the ſolid content in Inches.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherefore, Extend the Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es from 1, to 30 the breadth; the
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:59941:49"/>ſame will reach from 21.6 the depth, to 648 the content of the baſe. — Again, Extend the Compaſſes from 1, to 648 the content of the baſe; that extent will reach from 183 the length, to 118584 Inches the ſolid content. But ſo many places of Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures cannot well be eſtimated upon your Line, except. it be very large; but by following Examples you ſhall have your deſire accompliſhed exactly and eaſily.</p>
                  <p>Example 2. <hi>To finde the content of the ſame piece of Timber in Foot-meaſure, the dimenſions being given in Inches and parts.</hi> The proportion is,
<list>
                        <item>1. As 1, to 30 the breadth;</item>
                        <item>So 21.6 the depth, to 648 the content of the baſe, as before.</item>
                     </list>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:59941:50"/>
                     <list>
                        <item>2. As 1728, the number of ſolid Inches in a Foot of Timber, is to 648, the content of the baſe;</item>
                        <item>So is 183, the length in Inches, to 68 Foot, and 62/100 parts of a Foot, as before.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherefore, as before, Extend the Compaſſes from 1, to 30 the breadth; the ſame will reach from 21.6 the depth, to 648 the content of the baſe, as before.— Again, Extend the Compaſſes from 1728, to 648 the baſe, the ſame extent will reach the ſame way, from 183 the length, to 68.62 the content of the piece of Timber in Feet and parts, that is, 68 Foot, and above half a Foot.</p>
                  <p>Example 3. <hi>Let a ſquared Stone or piece of Timber be</hi> 30 <hi>Inches broad, and</hi> 21 <hi>Inches ſix parts deep; how much in length ſhall make a Foot
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:59941:50"/>ſquare of that piece of Timber or Stone?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>You may finde the content of the baſe, as in the laſt Example, to be 648 Inches; then the proportion is,
<list>
                        <item>As 648, the content of the baſe, is to 1728, the inches in a Foot;</item>
                        <item>So is 1, to 2 inches 67 parts, the length of a Foot ſolid.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Therefore, Extend the Compaſſes from 648 the baſe, to 1728; the ſame will reach from 1, to 2.67: So that 2 inches 67/100 parts will make a Foot ſolid of that piece of Timber or Stone.</p>
                  <p>This may be done another way by this Analogy or Proportion.
<list>
                        <item>1. As. 12, to 30 the breadth in inches;</item>
                        <item>So 21.6, the depth in inches, to a fourth number (which here will be about 54.)</item>
                     </list>
                     <pb n="72" facs="tcp:59941:51"/>
                     <list>
                        <item>2. As this fourth number 54, is to 144;</item>
                        <item>So is 1, to 2.67, the length of a Foot ſolid.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherefore, Extend the Compaſſes from 12, to 30 the breadth, that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent will reach from 21.6 the depth, to a certain place upon the Line (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout 54), where keep the point of the Compaſs faſt, and open the other to 144, then will this extent of the Compaſſes reach from 1, to 2 inches 67 parts, the length of a Foot ſolid, as before.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <head>II. <hi>In Foot-Meaſure only.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Example 1. <hi>Let a Stone, or a piece of Timber, be</hi> 2 <hi>Foot</hi> 50 <hi>parts broad,</hi> 1 <hi>Foot</hi> 80 <hi>parts deep, and</hi> 15 <hi>Foot</hi> 25 <hi>parts long, how many ſolid or cubical Feet doth ſuch a piece contain?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="73" facs="tcp:59941:51"/>
                  <p>The proportion is.
<list>
                        <item>1. As 1, is to 2.50 Foot the breadth;</item>
                        <item>So is 1.80 Foot the depth, to 4.50 Foot, the baſe in ſuch meaſure.</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <item>2. As 1, unto 4.50 the baſe;</item>
                        <item>So 15.25. the length, to 68.62, the content in Feet.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 1 to 2.50 the breadth; the ſame will reach from 1.80 the depth, to 4.50 the baſe.— Again, Extend the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes from 1, to 4.50 the baſe; that extent will reach from 15.25 the length, to 68.62, the content in Feet.</p>
                  <p>Example 2. <hi>In the forementioned piece of ſquared Stone or Timber, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> 2 <hi>Foot</hi> 50 <hi>parts broad, and</hi> 1 <hi>Foot</hi>
                     <pb n="74" facs="tcp:59941:52"/>80 <hi>parts deep, Let it be required to finde how much thereof in length will make a Foot.</hi> The proportion is,
<list>
                        <item>1. As 1, is to 2.50, the breadth;</item>
                        <item>So is 1.80, the depth, to 4.50, the content of the baſe in Foot-meaſure.</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <item>2. As 4.50, the baſe, is to 1;</item>
                        <item>So is 1 Foot, to 222 parts, the length of a Foot ſolid.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherefore, Extend the Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes from 1, to 2.50 the breadth; the ſame extent will reach from 1.80 the depth, to 4.50, the content of the baſe.— Again, Extend the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes from 4.50 the baſe, to 1; the ſame will reach from 10, to 222 parts, the length of a cubical or ſolid Foot of that Stone or piece of Timber.</p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:59941:52"/>
               </div>
               <div type="part">
                  <p>III. <hi>In FOOT-MEASURE and INCH-MEASURE together.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Example. <hi>Let a ſquared Stone or piece of Timber be</hi> 30 <hi>Inches broad,</hi> 27.6 <hi>Inches deep, and</hi> 15 <hi>Foot</hi> 25 <hi>parts long, how many cubical or ſolid Foot of Stone or Timber is shere in that piece?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The proportion is,
<list>
                        <item>1. As 1, is to 30 inches, the breadth;</item>
                        <item>So is 21.6 inches, the depth, to 640, the content of the baſe in inches.</item>
                     </list>
                     <list>
                        <item>2. As 144, the inches in a Foot ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perficial, is to 648, the content of the baſe in inches;</item>
                        <item>So is 15.25, the length of the piece in Foot-meaſure, to 68 Foot 62 part.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:59941:53"/>
                  <p>Wherefore, Extend the Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes from 1, to 30 the breadth, the ſame will reach from 21.6 the depth, to 648, the content of the baſe.— A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain, Extend the Compaſſes from 144, to 648 the content of the baſe, the ſame extent will reach from 15.25, the length of the piece, to 68.62, the ſolid content of the Stone or Timber in Feet and 100 parts of a Foot</p>
                  <p>By having the ſame things given in the ſame piece of Stone or Timber (or in any other) the work may be varied ſeveral ways: The Analogies or Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portions I will only give you, leaving the practiſe thereof to your ſelf.</p>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>Breadth of the piece 30 inches.</item>
                        <item>Depth of the piece 21.6 inches.</item>
                        <item>Length of the piece 15.25 foot.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="77" facs="tcp:59941:53"/>
                  <p>The Proportions.
<list>
                        <item>1. As 144, to 30, the breadth;</item>
                        <item>So 21.6, the depth, to a fourth Number.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>From which fourth Number, if you extend your Compaſſes to 1, and place one foot in 15.25, the length of the piece, the other Foot ſhall fall upon 68.62, the content of the Stone.</p>
                  <p>Or,
<list>
                        <item>2. As 12, unto 30, the breadth;</item>
                        <item>So 21.6, the depth, to ſome fourth Number.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>From this fourth Number, Extend the Compaſſes to 12, that diſtance will reach from 15.25, the length of the piece, to 68.62, the content of the piece.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="16" type="chapter">
               <pb n="78" facs="tcp:59941:54"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVI.</hi> How to meaſure <hi>Stone</hi> or <hi>Timber</hi> by the Line, by having the Square of the Baſe, and the Length of the Piece given, both in <hi>Foot</hi> and <hi>Inch Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>HOw to finde the length of a Side of a Geometrical Square, that ſhall be equal to any Parallelo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gram or Long Square, is taught at the latter end of the Tenth Chapter of this Book, by which Rule it may at any time be found: That being done there, I ſhall only here begin with Examples.</p>
               <pb n="79" facs="tcp:59941:54"/>
               <p>Example 1. <hi>There is a Squared piece of Timber whoſe length is</hi> 183 <hi>Inches, and the Side of the Square equal to the baſe or end thereof is</hi> 25 <hi>Inches</hi> 45 <hi>parts; how many Foot doth that piece contain?</hi>
               </p>
               <p n="1">
                  <list>
                     <item>1. As 41.57, to 25.45, the ſide of the Square;</item>
                     <item>So is 183, the length in Inches, to a fourth Number.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>2. And that fourth Number,</item>
                     <item>to 68.62, the content in Feet.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 41.57, to 25.45, the ſide of the Square; the ſame will reach from 183, the length, to ſome other part of the Line; from whence if you again extend the ſame diſtance, the point will reſt upon 68 Foot 62/100 parts of a Foot; and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Foot is in the piece.</p>
               <pb n="80" facs="tcp:59941:55"/>
               <p>Example 2. <hi>Let the ſide of a Square, equal to the Baſe of a piece of Stone or Timber, be</hi> 2 <hi>Foot</hi> 12 <hi>parts, and the length of the ſame piece</hi> 15 <hi>Foot</hi> 25 <hi>parts; how many ſolid Foot is there in that piece?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. As 1. to 2 Foot 12 parts the ſide of the Square;</item>
                     <item>So 15 Foot 25 parts, the length, to a fourth Number.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>2. And that fourth Number,</item>
                     <item>to 68.62, the content in Feet.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 1, to 2.12, the ſide of the Square; that will reach from 15.25, the length, to ſome other number on the Line, from whence the Compaſſes being extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the movable point will fall upon 68.62, the content, as before.</p>
               <pb n="81" facs="tcp:59941:55"/>
               <p>Example 3. <hi>The ſide of a Square, equal to the Baſe of a Stone, being</hi> 25 <hi>Inches</hi> 45 <hi>parts, and the length of that Stone</hi> 15 <hi>Foot</hi> 25 <hi>parts, how ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Foot doth it contain?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. As 12, to 25.45, the Square in Inches;</item>
                     <item>So is 15.25 Foot, the length, to a fourth Number.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>2. And that fourth Number,</item>
                     <item>to 68.62, the content.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 12, to 25.45 the ſide of the Square; the ſame will reach from 15.25, to ſome other point upon the Line, from whence the Compaſſes being extend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, the movable point will fall upon 68 Foot 62 parts, the content of the Stone.</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:59941:56"/>
               <p>Example 4. <hi>There is a piece of Timber whoſe ſide of the Square of the Baſe is</hi> 25 <hi>Inches</hi> 45 <hi>parts; how much in length of that piece will make a Foot ſolid?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1. As 25.45, the ſide of the Square, is to 41.57;</item>
                     <item>So is 1 Foot, to a fourth Number.</item>
                  </list>
                  <list>
                     <item>2. And that fourth Number,</item>
                     <item>to 6 Inches 67 parts.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Wherefore, Extend the Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes from 25.45 the ſide, to 41.57; the ſame will reach from 1, to ſome other point, from whence the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes being extended, will reach to 6.67, the length of a Foot ſolid of that piece of Timber.</p>
               <p>Example 5. <hi>The length of the ſide of a Square, equal to the Baſe of a
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:59941:56"/>piece of Timber being</hi> 2 <hi>Foot</hi> 12 <hi>parts, to finde how much in length of that piece will make a Foot ſolid in Foot-meaſure.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <list>
                     <item>As 2.120, the ſide of the Square, is to 1.000;</item>
                     <item>So is 1.000, to a fourth Number:</item>
                     <item>And that fourth Number,</item>
                     <item>to 0.471 parts of a Foot, to make a Foot ſquare.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 2.120 the ſide of the Square, to 1000; the ſame extent will reach from 1000, downwards, to ſome other point upon the Line, and from thence downwards, to 222 parts of a Foot; and ſo much in length will make a Foot ſolid.</p>
               <pb n="82" facs="tcp:59941:57"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb n="83" facs="tcp:59941:57"/>
               <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                  <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
               </gap>
            </div>
            <div n="17" type="chapter">
               <pb n="84" facs="tcp:59941:58"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVII.</hi> Concerning <hi>Timber</hi> that is bigger at one end than at the other, either Round or Square; and how to meaſure it.</head>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <head>I. <hi>For SQUARED-TIMBER.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>IN large Timber-trees, when they are ſquared, there is a great diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proportion between the Squares of both ends; wherefore ſome do uſe to take the Square of the middle of the piece for the mean or true Square; but this is not exact, though much uſed; but the beſt way is this: Finde by the Problem at the end of the tenth Chapter of this Book, the length of the ſide of a Spuare equal to both the
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:59941:58"/>ends of the piece, add theſe two ſides together, and take the half thereof for the true Square; and with that Square you may by the Rules of the laſt Chapter meaſure it as if it were perfectly Square.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II. <hi>For ROUND-TIMBER.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>The ordinary way uſed for the meaſuring of Round Timber, is to girt it about the middle with a Line, and to take one fourth part thereof for the ſide of a Square equal thereto: but this is falſe, though moſt men uſe it, Cuſtom having made it bear the face of Truth; for it is more in meaſure than in reality it ſhould be.</p>
                  <p>But the exact way of meaſuring of Round Timber (eſpecially if it be growing) is this: About the middle
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:59941:59"/>thereof, in ſome ſmooth place, girt the ſame about with a ſtring:</p>
                  <p>Then have you this proportion.
<list>
                        <item>As 1000, is to the number of Inches about;</item>
                        <item>So is 2821, to the length of the ſide of a Square equal thereunto.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>So if a Tree, being girt about, as aboveſaid, ſhould contain in circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference 47 Inches 13 parts:</p>
                  <p>If you extend the Compaſſes from 1000 to 47 Inches 13 parts, the ſame extent will reach from 2821, to 13 Inches 29 parts, which is equal to the ſide of a Square equal to that Tree, which being obtained, the Tree may be meaſured divers ways, according to the Examples in the laſt Chapter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="18" type="chapter">
               <pb n="87" facs="tcp:59941:59"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XVIII.</hi> Concerning the meaſuring of <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Solids,</hi> as <hi>Cylinders, Globes, Cones,</hi> and ſuch like.</head>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <head>I. <hi>Of the CYLINDER.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A <hi>Cylinder</hi> is a round Figure, of equal circumference in all parts thereof, as a ſtanding Pillar, a Rowl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing-ſtone for Garden-walks, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> To meaſure ſuch a Figure there are ſeve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral ways, both by having the circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ference given when it is ſtanding, or by having the diameter at the end thereof when it is lying, or by having the ſide of a Square equal to the baſe thereof.</p>
                  <div n="1" type="section">
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:59941:60"/>
                     <p>I. <hi>By having the</hi> Diameter <hi>given.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>Example 1. <hi>The Diameter being</hi> 15 <hi>Inches, how much in length makes a Foot?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>As 15 the diameter, to 46.90;</item>
                           <item>So is 1, to a fourth.</item>
                           <item>And that fourth,</item>
                           <item>to 9.78, the length of a Foot.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 15 the diameter, to 46.90; that extent will reach from 1, to another point upon the Line, and from thence to 9 Inches 78 parts, the length of a Foot ſolid.</p>
                     <p>Example 2. <hi>The diameter being</hi> 1 <hi>Foot</hi> 25 <hi>parts, how much in length makes a Foot in Foot-meaſure?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="89" facs="tcp:59941:60"/>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>As 1.25, the diameter in Feet, unto 1.128;</item>
                           <item>So 1, to a fourth number,</item>
                           <item>And that,</item>
                           <item>to 8.14, the length of a Foot ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid in Foot-meaſure.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 1.25 the diameter, to 1.128; the ſame will reach from 1, to ſome other num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, and from thence to 1 Foot 128 parts of a Foot.</p>
                     <p>Example 3. <hi>Having the diameter</hi> 15 <hi>Inches, and the length</hi> 105 <hi>Inches, how many ſolid Inches doth the Cylin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Contain?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>As 1.128, to 15 Inches the diameter;</item>
                           <item>So is 105 Inches, the length, to a fourth number,</item>
                           <item>And that,</item>
                           <item>to 18555.34 Inches, the content.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="90" facs="tcp:59941:61"/>
                     <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 1.128, to 15 the length; the fame extent will reach from 105 the length, to ſome other number, and from thence to 18555.34 Inches, the content of the Cylinder in Inches.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Example</hi> 4. <hi>Having the diameter</hi> 1 <hi>Foot</hi> 25 <hi>parts, and the length</hi> 8 <hi>Foot</hi> 75 <hi>parts, to finde the content in Feet.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>As 1.128, to 1.25, the diameter;</item>
                           <item>So 8.75, the length, to a fourth,</item>
                           <item>And that fourth,</item>
                           <item>to 10.74 Foot, the content.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 1.128, to 1.25 the diameter; that extent will reach from 8.75 the length, to ſome other number, and from that to 10 Foot 74 parts, the content.</p>
                     <p>Example 5. <hi>Having the diameter</hi>
                        <pb n="91" facs="tcp:59941:61"/>15 <hi>Inches, and the length</hi> 105 <hi>Inches, how many Foot doth it contain?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>As 46.90, to 15 Inches, the diameter;</item>
                           <item>So is 105 Inches, the length, to a fourth,</item>
                           <item>And that fourth,</item>
                           <item>to 10 Foot 74 parts, the content.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 46.90, to 15 the diameter; that extent will reach from 105, the length, to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther number, and from that to 10 Foot 74 parts, the content.</p>
                     <p>Example 6. <hi>The diameter being</hi> 15 <hi>Inches, and the length</hi> 8 <hi>Foot</hi> 75 <hi>parts, how many Foot doth it contain?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>As 13.54, to 15 Inches, the diameter;</item>
                           <item>So 8.75 Foot the length, to a fourth,</item>
                           <item>And that fourth,</item>
                           <item>to 10.74, the length in Feet.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="92" facs="tcp:59941:62"/>
                     <p>Extend the Compeſſes from 3.54, to 15 the length, that extent will reach from 8.75 the length, to ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther number, and from thence to 10.74 Foot, the content in Feet.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="section">
                     <head>II. <hi>By having the</hi> Circumference <hi>given.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>Example 1. <hi>The Circumference of a Cylinder is</hi> 47 <hi>Inches</hi> 13 <hi>parts, how much thereof in length ſhall make a Foot ſolid.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>As 47.13 Inches, the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, to 147.36;</item>
                           <item>So 1, to a fourth number,</item>
                           <item>And that,</item>
                           <item>to 9.78 Inches, the length of a Foot.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 47.13, the circumference, to 147.36; that
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:59941:62"/>extent will reach from 1, to a fourth number, and from thence to 9 Inches 78 parts, the length of a Foot ſolid.</p>
                     <p>Example 2. <hi>Having the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of a Cylinder</hi> 3 <hi>Foot</hi> 927 <hi>parts, to finde the length of a Foot ſolid thereof in Foot-meaſure.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>As 3.927 Foot, to 3.545;</item>
                           <item>So 1, to a fourth number,</item>
                           <item>And that,</item>
                           <item>to 815 parts of a Foot, the length.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 3.927, the circumference, to 3.545; that extent will reach from 1, to ſome o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther number, and from thence to 815 parts of a Foot, for the length of a ſolid Foot of that Cylinder.</p>
                     <p>Example 3. <hi>The circumference of a Cylinder being</hi> 47 <hi>Inches</hi> 13 <hi>parts,
<pb n="94" facs="tcp:59941:63"/>and the length thereof</hi> 105 <hi>Inches, how many Inches is there in ſuch a Cylin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>As 3.545, to 47.13, the circumference;</item>
                           <item>So 105 Inches, the length, to a fourth number,</item>
                           <item>And that,</item>
                           <item>to 18555, the content in Inches.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 3.545, to 47.13 the circumference; that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent will reach from 105 the length, to another number, and from thence to 18555, the number of ſolid Inches in the Cylinder.</p>
                     <p>Example 4. <hi>The circumference be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> 47 <hi>Inches</hi> 13 <hi>parts, and the length</hi> 105 <hi>Inches (as before); how many ſolid Foot in that Cylinder?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>As 147.36, to 47.13 Inches, the circumfer.</item>
                           <pb n="95" facs="tcp:59941:63"/>
                           <item>So 105 Inches, the length, to a fourth number,</item>
                           <item>And that,</item>
                           <item>to 10 Foot 74 parts, the content.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 147.36, to 47.13 the circumference, that extent will reach from 105 the length, to another number, and from that to 10 Foot 74 parts of a Foot, the ſolid content.</p>
                     <p>Example 5. <hi>Let the length of the Cylinder be</hi> 8 <hi>Foot</hi> 75 <hi>parts, and the circumference</hi> 3 <hi>Foot</hi> 927 <hi>parts; how many Foot doth it contain?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>As 3.545, to 3.927 Foot, the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence;</item>
                           <item>So 8.75 Foot, the length, to a fourth number,</item>
                           <item>And that,</item>
                           <item>to 10 Foot 74 parts, the content.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="96" facs="tcp:59941:64"/>
                     <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 3.545, to 3.927; the ſame extent will reach from 8.75 the length, to 10.74, the content in Feet.</p>
                     <p>Example 6. <hi>Let the circumference given be</hi> 47 <hi>Inches</hi> 13 <hi>parts, and the length</hi> 8 <hi>Foot</hi> 75 <hi>parts, how many ſolid Foot doth the Cylinder contain?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>As 42.54, to 47.13 Inches the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence;</item>
                           <item>So is 8.75 Foot, the length, to a fourth,</item>
                           <item>And that fourth,</item>
                           <item>to 10.74 Foot, the content.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 42.54, to 47.13 the circumference; that ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent will reach from 8.75 the length, to another number, and from thence to 10 Foot 74 parts, the content of the Cylinder in ſolid Feet.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <pb n="97" facs="tcp:59941:64"/>
                  <head>III. <hi>By having the Side of a</hi> Square, <hi>equal to the Baſe or End of a</hi> Cylinder.</head>
                  <p>Example. <hi>Let the Side of a Square, equal to the Baſe or End of the Cylin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, be</hi> 13 <hi>Inches</hi> 29 <hi>parts, and the length thereof</hi> 105 <hi>Inches; how many ſquare Feet are contained in that Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>linder?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>As 41.57, to 13.29 Inches, the ſide of the Square;</item>
                        <item>So is 105, the length in Inches, to a fourth number,</item>
                        <item>And that,</item>
                        <item>to 10 Foot 47 parts, the content of the Cylinder in Feet and parts.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 41.57. to 13.29 Inches, the ſide of a Square equal to the baſe of the Cylinder;
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:59941:65"/>that extent will reach from 105 Inch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, the length, to another number, and from thence to 10 Foot 47 parts, the content of the Cylinder in Feet.</p>
                  <div n="2" type="section">
                     <head>II. <hi>Of the CONE.</hi>
                     </head>
                     <p>A <hi>Cone</hi> is a round Figure, having for the baſe thereof a Circle, the ſide whereof riſeth from the circumference of the Circle round about the ſame equally, till it meet in a point juſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the centre of the Circle, and is in the form of a Spire-Steeple: And it is thus meaſured.</p>
                     <p>Example 1. <hi>Let there be a Cone the diameter of whoſe Baſe is</hi> 10 <hi>Inch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es, and whoſe height is</hi> 12 <hi>Inches; I would know how many ſolid or cubical Inches are contained therein.</hi>
                     </p>
                     <p>The diameter being 10 the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the Circle or Baſe will be found to the 78 Inches 54 parts; as
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:59941:65"/>by the fifth Example in Chap. 13. of this Book.</p>
                     <p>The Area of the Baſe being thus found, the proportion is,
<list>
                           <item>As 3, to 78.54 Inches, the content of the baſe;</item>
                           <item>So is 14 Inches; the height, to 314 Inches 16 parts of an Inch, for the content of the Cone in Inches.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 3, to 78.54 the baſe; that extent will reach from 12 the height, to 314 Inches 16 parts, the content of the Cone in ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid Inches.</p>
                     <p>Example 2. <hi>Let the diameter of the Baſe be</hi> 12 <hi>Inches, as before, and the length of the ſide he</hi> 13 <hi>Inches; kow many ſolid Inches is there in this Cone?</hi>
                     </p>
                     <pb n="100" facs="tcp:59941:66"/>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. Extend the Compaſſes from 1, to 5 Inches, half the diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of the Baſe, that extent will reach from 5 to 25.</item>
                        <item>2. Extend the Compaſſes from 1, to 13 the length of the ſide; that extent will reach from 13, to 169.</item>
                        <item>3. From this 169, take the 25 be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore found, and there remains 144.</item>
                        <item>4. Upon your Line take half the diſtance between 1 and 144, and you ſhall finde it to be 12, which 12 is the height of the Cone: So the height being had, you may finde the content, as in the laſt Example.</item>
                     </list>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III. <hi>Of SPHERICAL BODIES.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>A Spherical Body, is ſuch a Body, whoſe Superficies in all the parts of it are equally diſtant from the
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:59941:66"/>centre of the body; as Globes, Bul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lets, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Example 1. <hi>The Circumference of a Globe or Bullet being</hi> 28 <hi>Inches</hi> 28 <hi>parts, to finde the length of the dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>As 22, to 7;</item>
                        <item>So is 28.28, the circumference, to 9 Inches, the diameter.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 22, to 7; the ſame extent will reach from 28.28 the circumference, to 9 Inches, the length of the diameter of that Bullet.</p>
                  <p>Example 2. <hi>The diameter of a Spherical Body being given is</hi> 9 <hi>Inches, and its circumference is</hi> 28 <hi>Inches</hi> 28 <hi>parts, how many ſquare Inches is there in the ſuperficies of that Spherical Body?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="102" facs="tcp:59941:67"/>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>As 1, is to 9 Inches, the diameter;</item>
                        <item>So is 28.28 Inches, the circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence, to 254.5 Inches, the ſuperficial content.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 1, to 9 the diameter; the ſame extent will reach from 28.28, the circumference, to 254 Inches 5 parts, the ſuperfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Inches in this Spherical Body.</p>
                  <p>Example 3. <hi>The diameter of a Spherical Body being</hi> 9 <hi>Inches, how many ſolid Inches are therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. As 1, is to 9. the diameter;</item>
                        <item>Se is 9, to a fourth number,</item>
                        <item>And that fourth number,</item>
                        <item>to 729, the cube of the diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="103" facs="tcp:59941:67"/>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>2. As 9, the diameter, to 729, its cube;</item>
                        <item>So is 11, to 891 Inches, the ſolid con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the Spherical Body.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Extend the Compaſſes from 1 to 9, that extent will reach to 81, and from 81, to 729, the cube of the diameter.— Then, Extend the Compaſſes from 9, the diameter, to 729 its Cube; that extent will reach from 11, to 891 Inches, the ſolid content of the Spherical Body.</p>
                  <p>I might here add the manner how to meaſure other kind of Bodies, both Regular and Irregular; as <hi>Ellipſes, Parabolas, &amp;c.</hi> Alſo of <hi>Priſmes, Scalene Cones, Spheroiades, &amp;c.</hi> But theſe being out of the reach of ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Artificers, for whoſe ſakes this Treatiſe was chiefly compoſed, I
<pb n="104" facs="tcp:59941:68"/>ſhall here conclude this Treatiſe of the Uſe of the Line of Proportion, with a ſhort Supplement of Gauging of Veſſels.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="19" type="chapter">
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. XIX.</hi> Concerning the Gauging of <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>eſſels By the Line.</head>
               <p>BEfore you can meaſure your Veſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſel, to finde the content there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in Gallons or parts, you muſt finde the content thereof in ſolid Inches; and to effect this, you muſt finde the content of two third parts of a Circle, agreeable to the diameter at the Bung; and one third part of another
<pb n="105" facs="tcp:59941:68"/>Circle, agreeable to that of the dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter at the Head; theſe two added together, and multiplied by the length of the Veſſel, that product will be the content of that Veſſel in Inches.</p>
               <p>Example. <hi>Let there be a Veſſel whoſe</hi>
                  <list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>diameter at Head,</hi> 18</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>diameter at Bung,</hi> 32</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>length is</hi> 40</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>And let the content thereof, firſt in Inches, and then in Gallons, be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <head>I. <hi>For the two third parts of the</hi> Circle <hi>at the</hi> Bung.</head>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>As 1, to this univerſal number [5236];</item>
                        <item>So 1024, the ſquare of the diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at the Bung 32, to 536.166 Inches, which is two third parts of the content of the Circle at the Bung.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="106" facs="tcp:59941:69"/>
                  <p>Wherefore, Extend the Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes from 1, to 5236; the ſame extent will reach from 1024, (the ſquare of 32 the diameter at the Bung) to 536.166 inches, the content of two third parts of the circle at the Bung.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II. <hi>For one third part of the</hi> Circle <hi>at the Head.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>
                     <list>
                        <item>As 1, to this general number [2618];</item>
                        <item>So is 324, the ſquare of the dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meter at head 18, to 84.823 Inches, which is one third part of the content of the circle at the head.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherefore, Extend the Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes from 1, to 2618; the ſame extent will reach from 324 (the ſquare of 18, the diameter at the Head) to 84.823 Inches, the content of one third part of the diameter at the head.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <pb n="107" facs="tcp:59941:69"/>
                  <head>III. <hi>For the number of</hi> Square Inches <hi>in the</hi> Veſſel.</head>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Add theſe two numbers</cell>
                           <cell>536.166</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>and</cell>
                           <cell>84.823</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>They make</cell>
                           <cell>620.989</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>40</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>Which multiplied by 40, the length of the Veſſel, produceth</cell>
                           <cell>24839.560</cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>And ſo many Square Inches are con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained in ſuch a Veſſel, whoſe diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter at the Head is 18 Inches, at the Bung 32 Inches, and is 40 Inches long.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <pb n="108" facs="tcp:59941:70"/>
                  <head>IV. <hi>For the</hi> Content <hi>in</hi> Wine <hi>or</hi> Ale Gallons.</head>
                  <p>Divide this num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber 24839.56. by— 231 for Wine, 282 for Ale, and the Quotients ſhall tell you the number of Gallons and parts of a Gallon.</p>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell role="label">
                              <hi>Wine.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell role="label">
                              <hi>gall. parts.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>231)</cell>
                           <cell>24839.56</cell>
                           <cell>(107.52.</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>231</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>1739</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>1617</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>1225</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>1155</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>706</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>693</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>13</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="109" facs="tcp:59941:70"/>
                  <p>
                     <table>
                        <row>
                           <cell role="label">
                              <hi>Ale.</hi>
                           </cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell role="label">
                              <hi>gall. parts.</hi>
                           </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell>282)</cell>
                           <cell>24839.56</cell>
                           <cell>(88.08</cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>2256</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>2279</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>2256</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>2356</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>2256</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                        <row>
                           <cell> </cell>
                           <cell>100</cell>
                           <cell> </cell>
                        </row>
                     </table>
                  </p>
                  <p>By this work you may perceive that this Veſſel con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taineth
<list>
                        <item>107 Gallons 53 parts of Wine meaſure.</item>
                        <item>88 Gallons 08 parts of Ale meaſure.</item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p>How to multiply and divide by the Line, is taught in the Second and Third Chapters of this Book, and therefore were need<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs here to repeat it again: But
<pb n="110" facs="tcp:59941:71"/>I choſe rather to do it Arithme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tically, for the better illuſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and for the ſatisfaction of ſuch as have a delight in Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="measurement" type="treatise">
            <pb n="111" facs="tcp:59941:71"/>
            <head>
               <hi>How to Meaſure</hi> Board, Glaſs, Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, Stone, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <head type="sub">By a Line of Equal Parts, drawn from the Centre of a <hi>Two-foot Joynt-Rule.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>ALL Proportions that may be wrought upon a ſtraight Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ler by the Line of Proporti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on or Numbers, the ſame may be wrought by a Line of Equal Parts, drawn from the Centre of an opening Joynt.</p>
            <p>And whereas this Line of Equal Parts is numbered from the Centre of
<pb n="112" facs="tcp:59941:72"/>the Rule towards the end thereof, by 1, 2, 3, 4, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> to 10; that theſe Fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gures (as in the other Line) do ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times ſignifie themſelves only; ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>times 1, 2, 3, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> do ſignifie 10, 20, 30, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> ſometimes 100, 200, 300, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> according to the quality of the Queſtion propounded.</p>
            <p>By this Line you may alſo Multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply, divide, work the Rule of Propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and perform divers things which the Line of Numbers performeth, and ſome others which that will not; but I ſhall here only ſhew you how Board, Glaſs, Timber, Stone, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> may be thereby meaſured; which I ſhall do in theſe following Propoſitions. And,</p>
            <div n="1" type="part">
               <pb n="113" facs="tcp:59941:72"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>I.</hi> For SUPERFICIAL MEA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SURE, as <hi>Board, Glaſs,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>I.</hi> In INCH-MEASURE.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="proposition">
                     <head>
                        <hi>PROP. I.</hi> A Plank being <hi>27</hi> Inches broad, and <hi>263</hi> Inches long, how many Square Inches are contained therein?</head>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>As I, is to 27:</item>
                           <item>So is 263, to 7101.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Take in your Compaſſes the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from the Centre, to 27 (the breadth) upon your Line of Equal parts; with this diſtance ſet one foot in 10 at the end of the Line, and o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen the Rule till the other foot fall in 10 on the other Leg of the Rule.</p>
                     <pb n="114" facs="tcp:59941:73"/>
                     <p>The Rule thus ſtanding, take with your Compaſſes the diſtance between 263 on one Leg of the Rule, to 263 on the other Leg, this diſtance will reach from the Centre of the Rule to 7101; and ſo many ſquare Inches are in that piece.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="proposition">
                     <head>
                        <hi>PROP. 2.</hi> If a Board, or Plank, or piece of Pavement, or of Glaſs, be <hi>20</hi> Inches broad, how much thereof in length ſhall make a Foot ſquare?</head>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>As 20, is to 144;</item>
                           <item>So 1, to 7.2.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Take 144 out of your Line of E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>qual parts, from the Centre, and ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting one foot in 20, open the other Leg till the other Compaſs point fall in 20 alſo.</p>
                     <pb n="115" facs="tcp:59941:73"/>
                     <p>The Rule thus ſtanding, take the diſtance between 10 and 10, and that diſtance will reach from the centre of the Rule to 7 Inches 2/10 parts of an Inch; and ſo much in length will make a Foot Square.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>II.</hi> In FOOT-MEASURE.</head>
                  <div n="3" type="proposition">
                     <head>
                        <hi>PROP. 3.</hi> A Room is <hi>52</hi> Foot broad, and <hi>110.5</hi> Foot long; how many Square Foot are there in that Room?</head>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>As 52, is to 1;</item>
                           <item>So is 110.5, to 5746.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Take in your Compaſſes 52 the breadth; with this diſtance open the Ruler in 10, and 10; it ſo reſting, take the diſtance between 110.5 and
<pb n="116" facs="tcp:59941:74"/>110.5 on either ſide, that diſtance applied to the Centre of the Rule, will reach to 5746; and ſo many Square Foot is in that Room.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="proposition">
                     <head>
                        <hi>PROP. 4.</hi> A Plank being <hi>2</hi> Foot <hi>25</hi> parts broad, how much in length there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of ſhall make a Foot Square?</head>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>As 2.25, the breadth, is to 1 or 10;</item>
                           <item>So is 10, to 44, the length of a Foot.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Take in your Compaſſes the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from the Centre of your Rule to 1; then ſet one foot in 2.25, and open the other Leg till the other Compaſs point fall in 2.25 on the other ſide; the Rule thus ſtanding, take the diſtance between 10 and 10; that diſtance applied from the Centre
<pb n="117" facs="tcp:59941:74"/>of the Rule, will reach to 44 parts of a Foot; and ſo much in length will make a Foot.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>III.</hi> In YARD-MEASURE.</head>
                  <div n="5" type="proposition">
                     <head>
                        <hi>PROP. 5.</hi> A Room is hung with Tapeſtry, containing <hi>130</hi> Yards <hi>25</hi> parts in compaſs, and in depth <hi>5</hi> Yards <hi>20</hi> parts; how many Yards of Tapeſtry is in that Room?</head>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>As 1, to 5.20;</item>
                           <item>So 130.25, to 677.4.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Take 5.20 in your Compaſſes, and that diſtance put over in 10 and 10; the Rule thus ſtanding, take the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance between 130.25 and 130.25 on each Leg of the Rule, that di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance will reach from the Centre of the Rule, to 677 Yards 4 tenths of a Yard.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="part">
               <pb n="118" facs="tcp:59941:75"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>II.</hi> For SOLID-MEASURE, as <hi>Timber, Stone,</hi> &amp;c. By the Line of Equal parts.</head>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>I.</hi> In INCH-MEASURE.</head>
                  <div n="1" type="proposition">
                     <head>
                        <hi>PROP. I.</hi> A piece of Timber being <hi>30</hi> Inches broad, <hi>21</hi> Inches <hi>6</hi> parts deep, and <hi>183</hi> Inches long; how many Foot is contained in that piece of Timber?</head>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. As 1, is to 30;</item>
                           <item>So is 21.6, to 648.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Take the diſtance from the Centre to 30; then ſet one foot in 10, and open the Rule till the other Compaſs
<pb n="119" facs="tcp:59941:75"/>point fall in 10 on the other Leg of the Rule: Then take the diſtance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 21.6 and 21.6, that diſtance will reach from the Centre of the Rule, to 648, the content of the baſe or end of the piece of Timber in In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches: Then,</p>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>2. As 1728, the number of Inches in a Foot ſolid, is to 648, the content of the baſe;</item>
                           <item>So is 183 Inches, the length, to 68 Foot 62 parts, the content in Feet.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Take in your Compaſſes the di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance from the Centre to 1728, with this diſtance ſet one foot in 648, and open the other Leg of the Rule till the other point of the Compaſſes fall in 648 on the other Leg; then take in your Compaſſes the diſtance from the Centre to 183; with this diſtance
<pb n="120" facs="tcp:59941:76"/>move both points of the Compaſſes gently along on both the Lines on ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſide the Rule, till the Compaſs points reſt upon one and the ſame number on either Leg, which you ſhall here finde them to do at 68:62 parts; ſo the piece containeth 68 Foot and 62/100 parts of a Foot.</p>
                     <p>This kinde of work may ſeem trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bleſome at firſt; but little pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe will render it eaſie.</p>
                     <p>
                        <hi>Note.</hi> If you take the firſt number of your proportion from the centre of your Rule, you muſt take your third number thence alſo, and then will your number ſought be found as this here in this Example. But if you take your firſt number croſs the Rule, then your third number muſt be ſo taken alſo, and your number ſought muſt be taken from the centre, as thoſe before were.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="2" type="proposition">
                     <pb n="121" facs="tcp:59941:76"/>
                     <head>
                        <hi>PROP. 2.</hi> If a Stone be <hi>30</hi> Inches broad, and <hi>21</hi> Inches <hi>6</hi> parts deep; how much in length of that Stone will make a Foot ſquare?</head>
                     <p>You muſt firſt finde the content of the baſe, as in the firſt Propoſition, and it will be 648 Inches: Then,
<list>
                           <item>As 648, the content of the baſe, is to 1728, the Inches in a ſolid Foot;</item>
                           <item>So is 1, to 2.67 parts.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Take 1728 in your Compaſſes from the Centre; with that extent open the Rule from 648, to 648: The Rule ſo reſting, take the diſtance be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 10, and 10; that diſtance ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plied to the Line from the Centre,
<pb n="122" facs="tcp:59941:77"/>ſhall reach to 2 Inches 67 parts; and ſo much in length will make a Foot ſolid of that Stone or piece of Tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>
                     <hi>II.</hi> In FOOT-MEASURE.</head>
                  <div n="3" type="proposition">
                     <head>
                        <hi>PROP. 3.</hi> If a Stone or piece of Timber be <hi>2</hi> Foot <hi>50</hi> parts broad, <hi>1</hi> Foot <hi>80</hi> parts deep, and <hi>15</hi> Foot <hi>25</hi> parts long; how many ſolid Feet doth that piece contain?</head>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>1. As I, is to 2.50, the breadth;</item>
                           <item>So is 1.80, the depth, to 4.50, the content of the baſe in Feet.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Take 2.50 in your Compaſſes from the Centre; with that extent open the Rule in 10 and 10, then take the diſtance between 1.80 and 1.80, that
<pb n="123" facs="tcp:59941:77"/>extent will reach from the Centre of the Rule, to 4 Foot 50 parts, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent of the baſe.</p>
                     <p>
                        <list>
                           <item>2. As I, to 4.50, the baſe;</item>
                           <item>So 15.25, the length, to 68.62, the content in Feet.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Take 4.50 in your Compaſſes, and thereto open the Rule from 10 to 10; then take the diſtance between 15.25 and 15.25, that diſtance will reach from the Centre of the Rule, to 68 Foot 62 parts, the content of the Stone.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="4" type="proposition">
                     <head>
                        <hi>PROP. 4.</hi> The breadth being <hi>2</hi> Foot <hi>50</hi> parts, the depth <hi>1</hi> Foot <hi>80</hi> parts; how much in length thereof will make a ſolid Foot?</head>
                     <p>You may finde the quantity or con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent
<pb n="124" facs="tcp:59941:78"/>of the baſe by the firſt of the laſt Propoſition to be 4 Foot 50 parts: Then,
<list>
                           <item>As 4.50, the baſe, is to 1;</item>
                           <item>So is 10, or one Foot, to 222 parts.</item>
                        </list>
                     </p>
                     <p>Open the Compaſſes from the Centre to 1; then ſetting one foot in 4.50, open the other Leg till the Compaſs point falleth in 4.50 on the other Leg; then take the diſtance between 10 and 10, and that will reach from the Centre to 222: and ſo many parts of a Foot will make a ſolid Foot of that piece of Stone or Timber.</p>
                  </div>
                  <div n="5" type="proposition">
                     <head>
                        <hi>PROP. 5.</hi> To divide a Right Line into any number of Equal Parts, at the firſt opening of the Compaſſe.</head>
                     <pb n="125" facs="tcp:59941:78"/>
                     <p>Let a Line be given you to be di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into 6 equal parts: Take the length of the Line given in your Compaſſes: then becauſe it is to be divided into 6 parts, put one Foot in 6 on one Leg, and open the other Leg till the other point fall on 6 on the o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Leg: The Rule thus ſtanding, take the diſtance between 1 and 1, that diſtance ſhall divide your given Line into 6 equal parts: The like for any other number of parts whatſoever.</p>
                     <p>Many other Concluſions may be done by this Line; but I ſhall reſerve them, and divers other Concluſions of the like nature, to a more convenient place.</p>
                  </div>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
         <div n="line of proportion" type="treatise">
            <pb n="126" facs="tcp:59941:79"/>
            <head>The Uſe of the LINE of PROPORTION IMPROVED.</head>
            <head type="sub">
               <hi>By which</hi> Board, Glaſs, Land, Wainſcot, Hangings, Pavement, Brick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>work, Tyling, Plaiſtering, <hi>and any other</hi> Superficial; <hi>As alſo,</hi> Stone, Timber, <hi>and other</hi> Solid Meaſure; <hi>may be Meaſured thereby, without the Uſe of</hi> Pen, Inke, Paper, Compaſſes, <hi>or other</hi> Motion (<hi>as</hi> ſliding, <hi>or the like</hi>) <hi>whatſoever, by</hi> Inſpecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>only by looking upon the</hi> Line.</head>
            <div type="argument">
               <head>The ARGUMENT.</head>
               <p>I Am not ignorant how many have written of the Uſe of this Line of
<pb n="127" facs="tcp:59941:79"/>Proportion ſince the invention of Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garithms, from which Tables this Line is conſtitnted and made; as namely, After Mr. <hi>Gunter</hi>'s firſt contrivance, Mr. <hi>Wingate</hi> ſeconded him in ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king divers Lines to ſeveral Radiuſes, thereby to bring it to Extract the Square and Cube Roots without doubling or trebling, or dividing the diſtance into two or three parts; but this made a great number of lines to ſmall purpoſe; for nothing here could be done without the help of the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes.</p>
               <p>Again, One <hi>T. Browne,</hi> a Maker of Mathematical Inſtruments, made it in a Serpentine or Spiral Line, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed of divers Conſentrick Circles, thereby to enlarge the diviſions; which was the contrivance of one Mr.— <hi>Milburn</hi> a <hi>York-ſhire</hi> Gentleman, who writ thereof, and communicated his Uſes to the aforeſaid <hi>Brown,</hi> who (ſince his death) attributed it to him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf:
<pb n="128" facs="tcp:59941:80"/>But whoever was the contriver of it, it is not without inconvemence; for it can in no wiſe be made porta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble; and beſides (inſtead of Compaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes) an opening Joint with thirds muſt be placed to move upon the centre of the Inſtrument, without which no proportion can be wrought.</p>
               <p>There is yet a third way contrived, by which this Line is made very ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viceable, and convenient both for uſe and carriage, and is to be uſed with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Compaſſes, and is compoſed of two Lines of one length upon either ſide of two Rulers, to ſlide one by the ſide of the other; the uſes where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of in the meaſuring of <hi>Board, Glaſs, Timber, Stone, &amp;c.</hi> and in other parts of <hi>Geometry, Aſtronomy, Fortificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Trigonometry, Geography, Navi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, Gauging, Dialling, &amp;c.</hi> toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the uſes of the Lines of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tificial <hi>Sines</hi> and <hi>Tangents,</hi> in the ſame manner contrived, all upon one
<pb n="129" facs="tcp:59941:80"/>Ruler, are largely written upon by Mr <hi>Seth Partridge,</hi> in a Book of his late<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly publiſhed, entituled, <hi>The Deſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ption and Uſe of the Double Scale of Proportion;</hi> which Book and Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment are both ſold by Mr. <hi>Walter Hayes,</hi> at the Sign of the <hi>Croſs-Dag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers</hi> in <hi>Moor-fields,</hi> neer the <hi>Popes<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>head</hi> Tavern.</p>
               <p>There is yet another way of diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing of this Line of Proportion, by having one Line of the full length of the Ruler, and another Line of the ſame Radius broken in two parts be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween 3 and 4; ſo that in working your Compaſſes never go off of the Line: This is one of the beſt con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trivances, but here Compaſſes muſt be uſed.</p>
               <p>Theſe are all the Contrivances that I have hitherto ſeen of theſe Lines: That which I here ſpeak of, and will ſhew how to uſe, is only two. Lines of one and the ſame Radius, being ſet
<pb n="130" facs="tcp:59941:81"/>upon a plain Ruler of any length (the larger the better) having the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of one Line, at the end of the other, the diviſions of each Line be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſet ſo cloſe together, that if you finde any number upon one of the Lines, you may eaſily ſee what num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber ſtands againſt it in the other Line. This is all the Variation: and what this eaſie contrivance will effect, will appear by the uſes following.</p>
               <p>The Lines are the ſame with the Line of Proportion or Numbers, men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned and treated of in the former part of this Book; and therefore how to number upon them is ſhewed in the firſt Chapter of this Book, and therefore needs not here again be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peated. Alſo <hi>Multiplication, Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion,</hi> the <hi>Golden Rule, Duplicated</hi> and <hi>Triplicated Proportion,</hi> the <hi>Extracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of Roots, &amp;c.</hi> delivered in the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond, third, fourth, fifth Chapters, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> as alſo in Meaſuring of <hi>Superficies</hi> and
<pb n="131" facs="tcp:59941:81"/>
                  <hi>Solids,</hi> and the menſuration of other Figures treated of through the whole Book, theſe Lines thus diſpoſed will effect with Compaſſes: But ſome of thoſe Uſes which they will effect in meaſuring without the help of Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſes, I will here ſhew.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="caution">
               <head>CAUTION.</head>
               <p>What meaſure ſoever you meaſure by, let the Integer or grand Meaſure be divided into 10 or 100 parts (it matters not of what length your Lines of Proportion be, for to them all mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures are alike). Thus, If you mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure any thing by the Foot, let your Foot be divided into 100 parts: If by the Yard, divide your Yard into 100 parts: If by the Ell, divide that into 100 parts. So likewiſe, if by the Perch, Square, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> or by what Meaſure ſoever, let the grand Meaſure (as I ſaid before) be divided into 100 parts.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <pb n="132" facs="tcp:59941:82"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. I.</hi> OF SUPERFICIAL MEASURE,</head>
               <p>BY Superficial Meaſure is meant all kind of flat Meaſure, ſuch as is <hi>Board, Glaſs, Pavement, Hang<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings, Plaiſtering, Tyling, Land-mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, &amp;c.</hi> And theſe ſeveral things are meaſured by diſtinct Meaſures, as ſome by the Foot, others by the Yard, others again by the Ell, ſome by the Rod, and ſome by the Square: of all which I ſhall give Examples: and,</p>
               <div n="1" type="part">
                  <head>I. <hi>Of FOOT-MEASURE.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Example 1. <hi>If a Board be 2 Foot</hi>
                     <pb n="133" facs="tcp:59941:82"/>64 <hi>parts broad, how much in length of that Board will make a Foot Square?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Look upon one of your Lines (it matters not which) for 1 Foot 64 parts; and right againſt it on the other Line you ſhall finde 61: and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny parts of a Foot will make a Foot ſquare of that Board.</p>
                  <p>Example 2, <hi>A Plank is</hi> 3 <hi>Foot</hi> 50 <hi>parts broad, how much thereof in length will make a Foot?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Finde 3 Foot 50 parts upon one Line, and right againſt it on the other Line you ſhall finde 28 parts and 4/7 or ſomething more that half a part.</p>
                  <p>Example 3. <hi>If a Board be</hi> 75 <hi>parts of a Foot broad, how much thereof in length ſhall make a Foot ſquare?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="134" facs="tcp:59941:83"/>
                  <p>Look upon one of your Lines for 75, and right againſt it you ſhall finde 1 Foot, and 33 parts; and ſo much in length makes a ſquare Foot.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note.</hi> If the breadth of any thing given be more than one Foot, then the length of a Foot ſquare muſt be leſs than a Foot, as in the two firſt Examples it was: But if the breadth given be leſs than a Foot, (as in this laſt Example) then the length of a Foot ſquare muſt be more than a Foot.</p>
                  <p>Example 4. <hi>A Pain of Glaſs is</hi> 35 <hi>parts broad, how much in length makes a Foot?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Finde 35 in one Line, againſt it you ſhall finde 2 Foot 854/7 parts; and ſo much in length makes a ſquare Foot.</p>
                  <pb n="135" facs="tcp:59941:83"/>
                  <p>Example 5. <hi>A Pain of Glaſs is</hi> 3 <hi>Foot broad, how much in length makes a Foot?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Finde 3 Foot in one Line, againſt it in the other you ſhall finde 33 ⅓ parts, and ſo much in length makes a Foot ſquare.</p>
                  <p>Example 6. <hi>If a piece of Glaſs be</hi> 1 <hi>Foot</hi> 98 <hi>parts broad, how much in length will make a Foot?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Look 1 Foot 98 parts in one Line, and againſt it in the other you will finde 5 Foot and half a part, and ſo much in length makes a Foot.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="part">
                  <head>II. <hi>Of YARD-MEASURE.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Example 1. <hi>A Gallery is Wainſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted</hi> 2 <hi>Yards</hi> 56 <hi>parts deep, how much of that length will make a Yard ſquare?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="136" facs="tcp:59941:84"/>
                  <p>Seek 2 Yards 56 parts in one Line, and againſt it in the other you ſhall finde 39 parts and ſomewhat more; and ſo many parts of a Yard will make a Yard ſquare.</p>
                  <p>Example 2. <hi>A Room is Wainſcoted</hi> 1 <hi>Yard</hi> 13 <hi>parts high; how much in length thereof will make a Yard ſquare?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Look one Yard 13 parts in one Line, againſt it in the other you will finde 88 parts, and above half a part; and ſo much in length makes a Yard ſquare.</p>
                  <p>Example 3. <hi>If the Frieze about a Room be</hi> 62 <hi>parts of a Yard broad, how much in length there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of will make a Yard ſquare?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Finde 62 parts in one of your
<pb n="137" facs="tcp:59941:84"/>Lines, and againſt it in the other you ſhall finde 1 Yard 61 parts, and ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what more; and ſo much in length makes a Foot ſquare.</p>
                  <p>Example 4. <hi>There is a Gallery pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved with Marble, being</hi> 5 <hi>Yards</hi> 70 <hi>parts broad; how much of that in length will make a Yard ſquare?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Seek 5 Yards 70 parts in one Line, and againſt it in the other you ſhall finde 17 parts and an half; and ſo much in length of that Pavement will make a Yard ſquare.</p>
                  <p>Example 5. <hi>A Parlour being</hi> 7 <hi>Yards</hi> 29 <hi>parts broad, hath a Cieling of Fret-work plaiſtered, how much of that breadth will make a Yard Square?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Finde 7 Yards 29 parts in one of
<pb n="138" facs="tcp:59941:85"/>your Lines, and right againſt it in the other Line you ſhall finde 13 parts and 7/10, which is above half a part: So that 13 parts and a little more than half a part, will make a Yard ſquare of that Cieling.</p>
                  <p>Example 6. <hi>A Plaiſterer hath Rendered the inſide of a Wall containing</hi> 2 <hi>Yards</hi> 36 <hi>parts in height; how much of that will make a Yard ſquare?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Finde 2 Yards 36 parts in one of your Lines, and right againſt it on the other you ſhall finde 42 parts 3/10 of a part, that is ſomething more than one third part of a part; and ſo much in length makes a Yard Square.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="part">
                  <head>III. <hi>Of MEASURE by the ELL.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Example 1. <hi>There is a Room hung with Tapeſtry, which is</hi> 4 <hi>Ells</hi>
                     <pb n="139" facs="tcp:59941:85"/>25 <hi>parts high; how much Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peſtry in length will make an Ell ſquare?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note.</hi> Here by Ells we underſtand Flemiſh Ells (for by that Mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure are Hangings ſold); which Ell contains three quarters of our Yard; that is, 75 parts of our Yard: So that if an Up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>holſter have his Flemiſh Ell di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vided into 100 parts, he may meaſure his Hangings as in the Examples following is ſhewed.</p>
                  <p>Here becauſe the Hangings are 4 Ells 25 parts deep, Look for 4 Ells 25 parts in one of your Lines, right againſt which in the other you ſhall finde 23 parts and a half; and ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny parts of his Ell will make a Flemiſh Ell ſquare.</p>
                  <p>Example 2. <hi>T<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> Embroidery of a
<pb n="140" facs="tcp:59941:86"/>pair of Vallens about a Bed is</hi> 28 <hi>parts of a Flemiſh Ell deep; how much of that Embroidery in length will make a Flemiſh Ell ſquare?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Look for 28 parts in one of your Lines, and againſt it in the other Line you ſhall finde 3 Ells and 57 parts of an Ell; and ſo much in length will make an Ell ſquare.</p>
                  <p>Example 3. <hi>A Gallery being</hi> 3 <hi>Ells</hi> 98 <hi>parts deep, is hung with Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ras; how much of that depth will make an Ell ſquare?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Seek 3 Ells 98 parts in one Line againſt which in the other you ſhall finde 25 yarts and 1/10 of a part; and ſo much in length will make an Ell ſquare.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="part">
                  <pb n="141" facs="tcp:59941:86"/>
                  <head>IV. <hi>Of MEASURE by the ROD.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>Example 1. <hi>There is a Brick-wall which is</hi> 75 <hi>parts of a Rod high, how much in length of that Wall will make a Rod ſquare?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Note,</hi> That all Wall-work is by the Bricklayers meaſured by the Rod, which contains 16 Foot and a half in length: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, let his Rod, being 16 foot and an half in length, be divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded into 100 equal parts, and then let him work as followeth.</p>
                  <p>The Wall being 75 parts of a Rod high, Look for 75 parts in one Line, and in the other Line right againſt 75 you ſhall finde 1 Rod 33 parts of a Rod; and ſo much of that Wall in length is contained in a Square Rod.</p>
                  <pb n="142" facs="tcp:59941:87"/>
                  <p>Example 2. <hi>A Carpenter hath Rail'd and Paled in a Garden with Pales</hi> 52 <hi>parts of a Rod high, how much of that Paling ſhall make a Rod ſquare?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Seek 52 parts in one Line, againſt it in the other Line you ſhall finde 1 Rod 92 parts; and ſo much in length will make a Rod ſquare of that Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling.</p>
                  <p>Example 3. <hi>A Bricklayer hath made a Shewer to carry Water, the Bottom, Sides, and Arch together contains</hi> 1 <hi>Rod</hi> 64 <hi>parts; how much of that Drain or Shewer makes a Square Rod?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Finde 1 Rod 64 parts in one of your Lines, and right againſt that num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber you ſhall finde in the other Line almoſt 61 parts; and ſo many parts of a Rod in length will make a Rod ſquare.</p>
                  <pb n="143" facs="tcp:59941:87"/>
                  <p>And here note, That though I have here put theſe two laſt Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, that Paling is not meaſured by the Square Rod, but (let the height thereof be what it will) it is meaſured by the Rod in length. In like manner is Hedging, Ditching, and many other things that are meaſured by the Rod.</p>
                  <p>Example 4. <hi>If a piece of Land be</hi> 2 <hi>Rod</hi> 31 <hi>parts broad, how much in length thereof ſhall make a Rod ſquare?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Seek 2 Rods 31 parts upon one of your Lines, and over againſt it upon the other Line you ſhall finde 42 parts and about ⅓ of a part; and ſo much in length makes a ſquare Rod.</p>
                  <p>Example 5. <hi>A piece of Land be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> 80 <hi>parts of a Rod broad,
<pb n="144" facs="tcp:59941:88"/>how much thereof in length ſhall make a Rod ſquare?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Look for 80 parts in one Line, and in the other Line oppoſite thereunto you ſhall finde 1 Rod 22 parts, and ſo much in length makes a Rod ſquare.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="part">
                  <head>V. <hi>Of MEAS<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>RING by the SQUARE.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <p>There are two things principally which are meaſured by the Square, and they are Tyling of Houſes, and Flooring of Rooms; and in this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ckoning they account a Square to be 10 Foot every way: So that for this kind of Meaſure divide a Line or Rod of Ten Foot long into 100 parts, and it is fit for the purpoſe.</p>
                  <p>Exampler 1. <hi>A Barn, the breadth of the Tyling whereof on both ſides is</hi> 1 <hi>Square</hi> 30 <hi>parts, how
<pb n="145" facs="tcp:59941:88"/>much in length of that Tyling will make a Square Square?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Finde 1 Square 30 parts upon one of your Lines, and right againſt it on the other Line you ſhall finde 77 parts almoſt, and ſo much in length of that Tyling will make a Square Square.</p>
                  <p>Example 2. <hi>The Tyling of a houſe is</hi> 76 <hi>parts of a Square broad, how much in length thereof will make a Square Square?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Seek 76 parts in one Line, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt it in the other you ſhall finde 1 Square 31 parts and an half almoſt; and ſo much in length will make a Square Square, that is, 10 Foot every way, in all 100 Foot.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <pb n="146" facs="tcp:59941:89"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. II.</hi> OF SOLID MEASURE.</head>
               <p>BY Solid Meaſure is meant ſuch Meaſure as hath Length, Breadth, and Thickneſs, ſuch as Timber, Stone, or the like. But before Timber or Stone can be meaſured, you muſt finde the content of the ſquare of the baſe thereof, which is taught by the Problem at the end of the Tenth Chapter: but that being performed by Compaſſes, I will here ſhew how it may be (by theſe Lines thus diſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed) performed without; and that ſhall be my firſt Propoſition or Exam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple.</p>
               <p>Example 1. <hi>Let a piece of Timber or a Stone be</hi> 80 <hi>parts of a Foot
<pb n="147" facs="tcp:59941:89"/>deep, and 3 Foot 75 parts broad; how much in length of that piece will make a Foot ſquare?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Here (by any of the former Rules of Superficial Meaſure) finde at 80 parts broad how much in length will make a Foot, which you ſhall finde to be 1 Foot 25 parts: For,</p>
               <p>If you finde 80 parts, the depth of the piece, in one Line, againſt it in the other you ſhall finde 1 Foot 25 parts. Take 1 Foot 25 parts of your Foot Rule, and meaſure it along the breadth of the piece, which is 3 Foot 75 parts, and ſee how often it is con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tained therein, which you ſhall finde to be three times; wherefore, you may conclude, that the ſquare of the baſe of that piece of Timber whoſe depth is 80 parts, and whoſe breadth is 3 Foot 75 parts, is juſt 3 Foot.</p>
               <p>Now the ſquare of the baſe of the
<pb n="148" facs="tcp:59941:90"/>piece being thus obtained, you may finde the length of a Foot ſquare thereof in this manner.</p>
               <p>Example 2. <hi>Let the Square of the baſe of a piece of Timber or Stone be</hi> 3 <hi>Foot, how much in length of that piece will make a Foot ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lid?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Look for 3 Foot in one of your Lines, and in the other right againſt it you ſhall finde 33 parts and ⅓ part of a part; and ſo much in length will make a Foot ſolid.</p>
               <p>Example 3. <hi>Let a piece of Stone or Timber be</hi> 2 <hi>Foot</hi> 50 <hi>parts broad, and</hi> 50 <hi>parts deep; how much of that Stone in length ſhall make a ſolid Foot?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>By any of the ways before preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed you ſhall finde that the depth of
<pb n="149" facs="tcp:59941:90"/>your Stone being 50 parts, it will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire 2 Foot in length thereof to make a Foot ſquare: Wherefore, meaſure how often you can finde 2 Foot in the breadth of your Solid, which you may finde only once, and 50 parts more, which is one quarter of two Foot: Wherefore, the Square of this Solid contains 1 Foot 25 parts. Wherefore, Look in one of your Lines for 1 Foot 25 parts, and right againſt it you ſhall finde 80 parts; and ſo much in length will make a Foot ſolid.</p>
               <p>Example 4. <hi>The Square of the Baſe of any regular Solid being given, together with the length of the ſame Solid, to finde how many ſolid Feet are contained in the ſame.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let the forementioned Solid ſerve for this Example alſo, whoſe length
<pb n="150" facs="tcp:59941:91"/>was 35 Foot: We found that the Square of the Baſe was 1 Foot 25 parts, and that 80 parts in length would make one ſolid Foot: Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, take 80 parts of your Rule, and run it along the piece ſo often as you can, which you ſhall finde to be 43 and 60 parts, which is juſt three Quarters; ſo that in this piece of Timber there is 43 Foot and three Quarters.</p>
               <p>I might add many more Examples of this kinde, and ſome to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther purpoſes; but theſe are ſuf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficient for the purpoſe intended; and ſo I ſhall conclude this Treatiſe, leaving the farther pra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctiſe thereof to your ſelf: For,
<q>Uſus optimus Magiſter.</q>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="151" facs="tcp:59941:91"/>
               <head>
                  <hi>CHAP. III.</hi> OF CIRCULAR MEASURE.</head>
               <head type="sub">By having either the <hi>Circumfe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence</hi> or <hi>Diameter</hi> of any <hi>Circle</hi> given, thereby to finde the Side of a <hi>Square</hi> Equal to the ſame <hi>Circle;</hi> or the Side of a <hi>Square</hi> that may be inſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed within the ſame <hi>Circle.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>IN the Thirteenth Chapter of this Book you have ſix Examples by having the Circumference or Diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter of any Circle given, thereby to finde the Side of a Square equal, the Superficial Content, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> But I have
<pb n="152" facs="tcp:59941:92"/>ſeen upon ſome Two-Foot-Rules Lines to effect this thing by only o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pening the Compaſſes to the diſtance given upon one Line, and applying the ſame to ſome of the other Scales. One of thoſe Scales is noted at the end thereof with <hi>C,</hi> ſignifying the Circumference of any Circle; the other with <hi>D,</hi> ſignifying the Diame<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter; the other with <hi>S, E,</hi> ſignifying Square Equal to the Circie; the other with <hi>S. W,</hi> ſignifying Square within.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Example.</hi> So that if you ſhould have given you the Diameter of a Circle being 15 Inches, Out of the Line noted with <hi>D</hi> take 15 Inches, apply that diſtance to the Line noted with <hi>C,</hi> it will reach to 47 Inches and 13/100 parts of an Inch; and ſo much is the Circumference of that Circle.</p>
               <p>Again, The Diameter being 15 Inches, as before, take that diſtance out of the Line <hi>D,</hi> and it will reach upon the Line <hi>S E,</hi> to 13 Inches 29/100
<pb n="153" facs="tcp:59941:92"/>parts; and that ſhall be the Side of a Square equal to the Circle whoſe Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ameter is 15 Inches.</p>
               <p>Again, The Diameter being 15 Inches, if you take that diſtance out of the line noted with <hi>D,</hi> it will reach upon the Line <hi>S W,</hi> to 10 Inches 60/1 parts of an Inch; and that is the length of the Side of the greateſt Square that can be drawn within that Circle whoſe Diameter is 15 Inches.</p>
               <p>The like may be done if the Cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumference were given, by taking the Circumference thereof out of the Line noted with <hi>C,</hi> and applying it to the other Scales.</p>
               <p>This I thought convenient to adde here, becauſe ſometimes theſe Lines are put upon Two-foot Rules.</p>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
